<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief and plain discovery of the falseness and unscripturalness of anabaptism as the same is now practised by those of that perswasion, w[here]in are plainly proved from God's word the five particulars here handled, that God's covenant with Abraham, Gen. 17.7. is the Covenant of grace whereby all God's elect are saved ... / by Ja. Barry, an unworthy minister of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Barry, James, fl. 1650-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31095</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B968</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34200</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13977903</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13977903</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102079</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31095)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102079)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1560:66)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief and plain discovery of the falseness and unscripturalness of anabaptism as the same is now practised by those of that perswasion, w[here]in are plainly proved from God's word the five particulars here handled, that God's covenant with Abraham, Gen. 17.7. is the Covenant of grace whereby all God's elect are saved ... / by Ja. Barry, an unworthy minister of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Barry, James, fl. 1650-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 114 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained and torn, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102079:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102079:1"/>
            <p>A Brief and Plain DISCOVERY OF THE Falſeneſs and Unſcripturalneſs OF ANABAPTISM: As the ſame is now Practiſed by thoſe of that Perſwaſion: W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>in are (plainly) Proved, from God's Word, the Five Particulars here Handled.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That God's Covenant with <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 17.7. is the Covenant of Grace, whereby all God's Elect are Saved.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That Circumciſion was the Initiatory Seal of that Covenant to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Church-Seed, during that Diſpenſation.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That, Water-Baptiſm is now (under the Goſpel) ſucceeded in the room thereof.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. That the <hi>Gentile</hi> Believers and their Infant-Seed, have as Real a Right to the ſame Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, and the Seal thereof, as had <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Infant-Seed.</p>
            <p n="5">V. That Sprinkling (or Pouring-out) Water, on the Subject of Baptiſm, is the (Undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) Right Way of Adminiſtring Baptiſm under the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Ja. Barry,</hi> an Unworthy Miniſter of the Goſpel</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:102079:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102079:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Impartial and Unprejudiced READER, Who deſires to be Rightly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd in the Nature and Deſign of God's Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> (his Friend) in the behalf of Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and all his Eccleſiaſtical (or Church) Seed, both among <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> to the End of the World.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF the Spirit of Grace Reigns in thy Heart, thou wilt (I doubt not) readily believe me, (eſpecially when I moſt Solemnly Profeſs, as if I were (immediately) to be call'd to the Bar of the Great Judge) that no Prejudice ('or Hatred) againſt the Perſons of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who (without any Warrant from God's Word) Style themſelves Baptiſts, and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd Churches of Chriſt, hath ſtirr'd me up to appear in Print, in Oppoſing thoſe Pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Principles, which the Men of that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion do (with ſo much Violence and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptural
<pb facs="tcp:102079:3"/> Zeal) Teach and Maintain. I ſincerely Bleſs God, that his good Spirit hath taught me to diſtinguiſh between Perſons, and the Errors which they hold and maintain. Their Perſons I love, and am really griev'd, that I love them no more than I do. And I hope neither they nor any others will be Angry with me for ſo doing: But their Errors (in Religion) I do from my Heart abominate and loath, becauſe hateful to God, and all good Men, who know and underſtand them ſo to be. And for thus doing, I neither fear a Frown from God, nor yet Blame from any Man, (tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-wiſe) who is able to diſtinguiſh Truth from Error.</p>
            <p>That I ſhall be Cenſur'd and (uncharitably) Reflected on, for what I have done, in Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this ſmall Tract, I am not Inſenſible: I am very ſure none will thus do, but ſuch as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their know not, or care not what they ſay.</p>
            <p>Theſe kind of Blows I am taught to ward off with a Religious Scorn and a Holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; reſoluing (in Chriſt's Strength) to purſue and hold faſt the Truth of God, let who will Bark and Cavil againſt it. It was the ſaying of <hi>Valerius Maximus, Aequo Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ferenda ſunt, Imperitorum Convitia, &amp; ad Honeſta vadenti, Contemnendus eſt, Iſte Contemplus. The Reproaches</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of the Ignorant and Unskilful are to be born with an even (or patient) Mind: And
<pb facs="tcp:102079:3"/> he that intends to advance towards Good and Honeſt things, muſt Contemn their Contempt.</hi> That ſomewhat will come out in anſwer hereto, I queſtion not, (if the Men of that Principle have not loſt their old Wont) but (my Comfort and Confidence being built on the Rock of Ages) I never fear a Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from any (nay all) of that Perſwaſion, who Breath on the Earth, until they procure (from Heaven) another Goſpel, which is (Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ametrically) oppoſit to the Goſpel delivered by the Son of God, which I am ſure will never be.</p>
            <p>I have made no Deviation from the good old Way chalkt out by <hi>Abraham</hi>'s God, (wherein the Prophets and Apoſtles, with all the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Churches, who are gon to Heaven, walkt in) that I know of: If I have, I do faithfully promiſe, that (upon the diſcovery of my Error) I will own my ſelf therein miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
            <p>I have been (for ſeveral Years paſt) impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tun'd by many Serious and Godly Chriſtians, to Print what now I expect to be Blam'd for, but never found my ſelf (thereto) inclin'd, till of late (not that I Queſtion any part of what I have Printed, being God's Truth; but (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) the variety of Tryals and ſharp Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e (Inceſſantly) followed me, ſince call'd to the Sacred Office, both in my Native City <hi>(Dublin)</hi> and alſo in <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:102079:4"/> have kept me back; together with my own great Averſion to appear in Print, in any Matters Controverſal. But obſerving (of late) how ſtrangely Anabaptiſm ſpreads both in City and Country; and being fully convinc'd, that Ignorance of (and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nacquaintedneſs with) the Covenant of Grace, was (and ſtill is) that which hath given advantage to the Preachers of that Way, in drawing Proſelites after them, I have (in Conſcience of my Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, both to God and Men) Improv'd my poor Talent, in Explaining and Opening up the Nature and Deſign of the Covenant of Grace, made with <hi>Abraham</hi> in <hi>Gen. 17.7.</hi> in hopes, that God will Bleſs the Plainneſs and Brevity therein us'd, to inform poor Ignorant (and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nthinking) Souls, how wretchedly they are impoſed upon, by Preachers of that Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who have (themſelves) as great need to be Inſtructed and Taught, what the deep My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Covenant of Grace be, as the poor (Tongue-ty'd) Bades, whom they (in vain) Labour to exclude and ſhut out from the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and Seal of that Covenant, in the Viſible Churches of Chriſt. As their denying <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Covenant, to be the Covenant of Grace, adminiſters juſt ground of ſuſpecting, whether they have any other than dark and confus'd Notions about the Doctrine of God's Free Grace, (ſo much ſpoken of in Pulpit and Print.)</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:102079:4"/>
            <p>So their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmercifulneſs and Hard-hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Infants of Believing Parents, in not allowing ſuch to be accounted of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of God's Elect, meerly becauſe of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacity of ſuch, to make an open Profeſſion of Faith and Repentance themſelves, adminiſters juſt ground of ſuſpecting whether they be Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox in the Doctrine of Election. I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſure the State of Infancy can neither null or make void the Electing Decree of God, nor yet render the Elect Infant any way uncapable of that Grace of God's Covenant, to which he is Elected, or of the Seal of that Covenant of Grace in the Church Viſible; for any to hold or ſay it doth, is to Reflect on the moſt High God, and to make him a mutable Agent, like to a Fickle Man, contrary to <hi>Mal. 3.6. Rom. 11.29.</hi> and (unavoidably) to ſend all Elect Infants to Hell, (who Die Infants) contrary to <hi>Mar. 10 14. Jo. 6.39. Rom. 11.7.</hi> All that I ſhall farther ſay, is only to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eg and Pray thee, for the Lord's ſake, for thy own Souls ſake, and for that Love and Tenderneſs, which the Law of Nature (eſpecially that of Grace) obliges thee to have for poor Infants, (if thou be a Parent) conſider well, and weigh Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly (in the Ballance of God's Sanctuary) the Arguments laid down in this ſmall Tract, to prove what I have (therein) undertaken. If God Bleſs the Reading thereof, to the keeping thee back from Eſpouſing the Errors herein
<pb facs="tcp:102079:5"/> decry'd; or if it ſhould prove the occaſion of thy Vomitting up (by ſound Repentance and hearty Reformation) the love and liking thou haſt had to thoſe Principles of Darkneſs, give God the Glory of his own Grace, and ſuffer thy ſelf no longer to be impos'd on by ſuch Preachers, who are not only Intruders into the Sacred Office, but alſo Heterodox and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound, in what they Teach concerning God's Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> being a Covenant of Works, concerning Infants-Baptiſm, being but a Popiſh Invention, and a piece of Will-Worſhip; and what they Teach and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently Affirm of Dipping, being the only right Mode of Baptizing Commanded by Chriſt, and Practiſed by <hi>John</hi> and all the firſt Baptizers: By which Principles they Raſe the very Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Salvation to Grown Believers, as well as to their Infants: And diſown, that Chriſt hath any right Goſpel Churches but themſelves: From which Principles I ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſay, and heartily pray, <hi>Good Lord De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me, and all the Families of thy Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful People.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:102079:10"/>
            <head>THE INTRODUCTION. An occaſional Diſcourſe between a Miniſter and a Church Member, concerning In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm; wherein ſundry material Queſtions are put by the Church Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and plainly and particularly An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by the Miniſter, for the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Ignorant, and the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſuch as are ſtaggering in their judgments, about the lawfulneſs of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants-Baptiſm.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brother</hi> Edward, <hi>By what I have heard from ſome of my Neighbours, as alſo by the diſcourſe which paſt between you and me when laſt together, I ſuſpect that ſome have been tampering with you, to draw you away to Anabaptiſm; is it ſo or no? deal plainly, to the end I might addreſs my ſelf to my duty, in giving you ſatisfaction herein, from Gods Word.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Church Member.</speaker>
               <p>I muſt ingeniouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge Sir, that I am not without wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, and doubtful thoughts in my Mind about Infant-Baptiſm, occaſioned partly, by diſcourſing with ſome of that way and perſwaſion; partly, by reading ſome Books which were put into my hand; which, to me
<pb facs="tcp:102079:11"/> ſeems full of clearneſs, that Infant-Baptiſm is no way warrantable or juſtifiable by the Goſpel of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Miniſt. <hi>I find then that I am not miſtaken in my apprehenſion of you in this matter: but for your encouragement, I muſt tell you, that you are but tryed herein by a temptation; for which I think never the worſe of your Souls ſtate, neither are my hopes and confidence of your integrity towards God, a jot or whit leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſened by the inclination in your Mind to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that Opinion; for I have known ſome ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Holy and upright Hearted Chriſtians, who in the ſimplicity of their Hearts have ſtrongly enclined to favour and eſpouſe that cauſe and principle, as the moſt plauſible and likely to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the Goſpel, there being no mention at all of Infant-Baptiſm in the Goſpel, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Precept, nor yet in Example, to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it; yea, I my ſelf have (in my firſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out in the ways of Chriſtianity) met with temptations to draw me to that Opinion; and that by the very ſame means which hath occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned your ſtaggering herein. And the main things which induced me to hanker after that Principle, were,</hi> (1.) <hi>The high and charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble opinion I had of ſome of that Party, being Men of high attainments in Grace and Goſpel Holineſs.</hi> (2.) <hi>There appearing to me no command for Infant-Baptiſm in all the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, nor yet any one inſtance where it is ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:102079:5"/> that ſuch were Baptized.</hi> (3.) <hi>The many Quotations of Learned Divines and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, which the Anabaptiſts Books aſſured me were all of their Judgment and Perſwaſion herein; which much ſtartled, and ſway'd me to kind apprehenſions of their way.</hi> (4) <hi>Their Branding Infant-Baptiſm with the Black Brand of Will-worſhip and Popery; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt both which I always had (ſince I knew Chriſt in the Goſpel of his Grace) and ever ſhall have (I humbly hope in Chriſt) a Mortal Diſlike, and rooted Hatred. By means of the</hi> 4 <hi>particulars now mentioned, I was drawn to the very verge or brink of Anabaptiſm, being juſt on the point of renouncing my Baptiſm (received in my Infant State) as being a meer Nullity or no Baptiſm at all. My roving Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit thus fluctuating and toſſing between the Waves and Billows of doubtful and diſtracting Cogitations: what I had beſt to do in this Caſe? whether to offer my ſelf to be Dipt, yea, or not? or to addreſs my ſelf to Miniſters of the contrary Judgment for reſolution (in ſo weighty and material a point:) Matters being thus, I providentially and happily happened into the Company of ſome of the Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Perſwaſion, Men no whit inferiour to thoſe I ſo much admired, (for Piety) and Holineſs, and who (I very well knew) were able to inſtruct and teach the others for matter of Learning, and deep knowledge in the Myſteries of the
<pb facs="tcp:102079:6"/> Goſpel: Theſe debating ſundry points in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy between the Anabaptiſts and the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, Proteſtant, Reformed Churches, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Infant-Baptiſm; I apprehended and ſaw ſo far into the Myſtery of Baptiſm, that I was at a ſtand, and began to queſtion whether I was not under a deluſion in diſliking my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm, received in Infancy; by means hereof I was ſtirred up to Pray earneſtly to God, that his good Spirit might teach and guide me in the way of Goſpel-Truth; which was ſeconded by a diligent ſearch into the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, and a careful reading and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Arguments brought by both Parties, both for and againſt Infant-Baptiſm. And in a ſhort time (through the ſpecial aſſiſtance of the Spirit of Chriſt) I was enabled to ſee and underſtand that there was nothing of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid weight in the Reaſons brought againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm, but what are in reality repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and contradictory to the Word of God: as will (I hope) in time, moſt plainly appear to your underſtanding. I have been the more prolix in ſpeaking my experience herein, that you might become ſenſible, that even Godly Men might be entangled in erronious Opinions. And to let you know what be the ordinary means to eſcape the Nets of Crafty Men, who lye in wait to enſnare poor, unſtable, (though Honeſt and well meaning) Souls. Now, as Chriſt (my Lord and Maſter) ſaid to</hi> Peter, <hi>after
<pb facs="tcp:102079:6"/> his recovery from his fall:</hi> When thou art Converted ſtrengthen thy Brethren, <hi>Luke</hi> 22. <hi>So, I am now come as my Duty binds me, to endeavour your recovery, and full ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in theſe points, about Infant-Baptim, wherein you ſeem to ſtagger.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Church Memb.</speaker>
               <p>I hope I can ſay (through ſpecial Grace) that I am no way fond of Errour: But what I do herein, I do it real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from my Conſcience, according to the light thereof: I hope (Sir) you will not blame me for acting according thereto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am far from arraigning your integrity to God, (being very ſenſible that herein you are but under a temptation, as ſtronger Chriſtians than you or I have been, and now are; neither ſhall I (in the leaſt) at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to preſs you to act herein againſt your Conſcience: Conſcience (I am ſenſible) is a tender thing, which is to be informed, not vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently impell'd or forced. I hope you have the ſame Charity for me, as to believe that what I do act in Baptizing the Infant-Seed of encovenanted Parents, and Pleading for ſuch; I do the ſame from my Conſcience, being ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded that what I do herein, is accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Word of God: But though I do not take on me to force or Lord it over your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, I hope you will (without offence) give me leave to uſe the freedom of a Paſtor with you, in doing two things, in order to recover
<pb facs="tcp:102079:7"/> you. The firſt is, to reprove you for going out of the way of Duty, in expoſing your Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to thoſe Soul deluding entanglements, which hath occaſioned your preſent diſturbance, and unſettledneſs in your Principles, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding entanglements; I mean your going out of the way of your Calling, to ſtare and gaze (out of curioſity) at the plunging of Perſons under the Water; which (albeit you and others may think may be done without either offence to your Brethren, or any kind of danger to your ſelf) hath in it an infatuating, charming Energie, to allure and draw into a liking of it. Your frequent diſcourſing with Men of that Principle, who (you very well know) glory not a little in Proſelyting People to that way: And your ſo much delighting to Read their Books, being not able to grapple with ſuch ſubtle Enemies; the Deceipt of whoſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments lyes covered under a falſe Vizzard. By theſe your Practiſes you have filled the Eyes of your Conſcience ſo full of that duſt and ſmoak, which is always raiſed by doubtful Diſputations; that for want of your Monitor, (your Conſcience I mean) you are now at an apparent ſtand in thoſe ways of Truth wherein you ought to run ſwiftly; and well it were if you had been at a ſtand before you had ſo far advanced in theſe unſcriptural Tenents: But however, ſeeing you are not aſcended ſo high (in theſe Errors) as to be Seated in the Scorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers-Chair,
<pb facs="tcp:102079:7"/> to laugh at and deride Baby-ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, as a piece of Will-worſhip and meer Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery; as the Anabaptiſts are well known to term and account Infant-Baptiſm: (Not for want of ignorance and prejudice, the Lord knows.) I ſhall now in the ſecond place endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to help you out of this Quagmire, into which your own incautelouſneſs and ſinful cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity hath (by the Art of a ſubtle Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) involved you: in order then to a ſpeedy helping you herein, I deſire you will reduce thoſe things wherein you deſire to be ſatisfied (about Infant-Baptiſm) to as few Heads, (and in as plain a method) as you poſſibly can; and then I ſhall endeavour to Anſwer your Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; wherein (I faithfully promiſe you) I ſhall moſt freely refer my ſelf to the Word of God, and to the Writings of thoſe Divines now in Glory: At whoſe Writings the Wiſeſt of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts are glad to light their Candle, though in the point of Baptiſm they are accounted neither able nor worthy to teach them. And when you and I are come to Concluſion, You in Objecting, and I in Anſwering, it will then appear whether Infant-Baptiſm be any part of Will-worſhip or meer Popery, as it is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by its Adverſarys.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Church Memb.</speaker>
               <p>Sir! I like your Propoſal very well, and in complyance with your reaſonable Requeſt, as alſo in order to my own ſatisfaction, I ſhall reduce thoſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars
<pb facs="tcp:102079:8"/> wherein I deſire to be ſatisfied, to 3 General Heads; under each of which I hope you will give me liberty to Propoſe (by way of Objection,) what I think convenient and fit to ſtart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I like very well to hear you name but</hi> 3 <hi>General Heads; I hope you will obſerve Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Method in what you intend to Object under thoſe</hi> 3 <hi>Heads.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Church Memb.</speaker>
               <p>I will obſerve Order and Method as well as I can; and ſhall (I hope) with becoming Candor, weigh in the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of an impartial and unprejudicate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration and judgment, what ſtrength ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be in your Anſwer; and in caſe I find my Conſcience ſatisfied by the ſtrength of your Anſwer, I ſhall readily own it, and give Glory to God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I deſire you to name the</hi> 3 <hi>General Heads, for fear we ſhould forget them when we come to be earneſt in our Diſpute.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Church Memb.</speaker>
               <p>The 3 General Heads which I propoſe to be ſatisfied in, are as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, (1.) The Covenant which God made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> mentioned in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. (2.) The Seal of that Covenant. And (3.) The Subjects who have a viſible Right to that Covenant and the Seal thereof. Under theſe 3 Heads (I ſuppoſe) may be brought in all that I need to ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:102079:8"/>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>As touching your firſt General Head,</hi> (viz.) <hi>The Covenant which God made with</hi> Abraham, <hi>What would you be at, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Church Memb.</speaker>
               <p>I would pray you to clear it up from the Word of God, that that Covenant is a Covenant of Grace, and not a Covenant of Works; for the apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I always had (till of late) that that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant was the Covenant of Grace, was the foundation whereon my former Principle, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Infant-Baptiſm was founded; but being informed and taught otherwiſe, both by Mens Preaching, and alſo by their Books. I am much in doubt as touching the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Infant-Baptiſm.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I perceive then you apprehend that Infant-Baptiſm is like to ſtand or fall, as the Covenant of God with</hi> Abraham, <hi>is proved to be either a Covenant of Grace or otherwiſe; what if it be made good from the Word of God, that the Covenant of God with</hi> Abraham <hi>is a Covenant of meer Grace.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Church Memb.</speaker>
               <p>Truly, to be plain and ingenious, I cannot ſee how Infant-Baptiſm can ſtand, if that Covenant be a Covenant of Works; as I am ſenſible the Baptiſts hold and teach it is; and which I am incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (under my preſent light) to judge it muſt be as they ſay. But in caſe it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved otherwiſe, I plainly ſee the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts
<pb facs="tcp:102079:9"/> are like to ſuffer a miſerable Shipwrack; for their holding and teaching that Gods Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> is a Covenant of Works, is the principal Pillar, on which almoſt all their Arguments againſt Infant-Baptiſm lean. If that Pillar then be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and overthrown by Scriptural Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the whole ſtructure will tumble of courſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am very glad that You and I do (in any meaſure) agree in our Sentiments about this matter; To let you ſee then, how Sandy a foundation the Anabaptiſts Build on, I ſhall bgin to lay down ſome Scriptural Arguments, to prove them moſt heterodox and unſound in this point of</hi> Abraham's <hi>Covenant; wherein they do moſt evidently raſe the very founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Life and Salvation to</hi> Abraham <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and all his Seed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102079:9"/>
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Of God's Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> wherein is plainly proved, that that Covenant, in <hi>Gen. 17.7.</hi> is the Covenant of Grace.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THat God's Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. was, and ſtill is, the Covenant of Grace, diſpenſed in a Church way: None of the Orthodox ever did, (or do) deny, that I can find, That the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that Covenant in this Senſe, is the Foundation Principle, on which all ſound Proteſtants, do maintain and juſtifie, the Right of Believers Infants to Baptiſm, is beyond contradiction.</p>
            <p>When the Moſt High, and Soveraigne Lord God ſaw fit to make known his Will and Pleaſure, to be; that his Covenant of Grace, (agreed on, between himſelf, and his Son Chriſt in Eternity) ſhould be Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed in an Eccleſiaſtical (or Church) way, he ſingles out (above all other men) <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> his Friend; on whom he Confers the Honourable Title, of the <hi>Father of the Faithful,</hi> Rom. 4.11. Not that <hi>Abraham</hi> did, or could (poſſibly) Beget a Believer (as ſuch) or could convey into the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren he Begat (according to Fleſhly Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102079:10"/> that Noble Grace of Faith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God's Free-Gift had Bleſſed himſelf. But God opens and propounds his Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant of Grace and Salvation to him, as a Publick Perſon, who was to Perſonate all true Believers; who (in after Ages) were to be Members of his Viſible Churches, to the ſecond coming of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Sum and Subſtance of that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, is briefly comprehended in the Words of <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. <hi>I will Eſtabliſh my Covenant between me and thee, and thy Seed after thee; in their Generations, for an Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant; to be a God to thee, and to thy Seed after thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Covenant hath <hi>Two</hi> Eſſential Parts, as all Right Covenants have, (1.) God's part, held forth in the Words, <hi>I will be a God to thee, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The meaning whereof (according to the Analogie of Faith,) muſt be thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. Tho' thou <hi>Abraham,</hi> whom I now call, to become my Friend and Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and a Publick Head (or Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive) of all believing Church Members, to the end of the World; be'ſt an undon and guilty ſinner, polluted in thy Nature, and born under <hi>Adam</hi>'s Covenant of Works; liable and obnoxious to its Curſe, and to the Wrath to come; unable to recover or help thy ſelf out of that deplorable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102079:11"/> into which thy natural Birth (as <hi>Adam</hi>'s Child) hath put thee. And albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, thou be no way worthy of any Favour, yet I think fit, to let thee know, what thoughts and purpoſes of Mercy and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I have in ſtore for thee, <hi>Abraham:</hi> And for the Reſt of mine Elect, whom I have Choſen to my ſelf in Chriſt, (the Promiſed Meſſiah,) of whom, that Son which I have Promiſed thee, is to be a Type: And in whoſe Perſon, all mine Elect, are to be Allegorically (or Typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally) Repreſented; and that, as thy Son is to be a Type of mine, in whom I have Elected and Choſen them.</p>
            <p>I frankly and freely Pardon and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give thee, all thoſe Tranſgreſſions and Sins, wherewith, (as <hi>Adam</hi>'s Child) thou ſtandeſt Chargeable, for breaking that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Works I made with <hi>Adam,</hi> thy (and all Mankinds) Natural and Faederal Head.</p>
            <p>I Account thee perfectly Juſt and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in my ſight; not by, or for, that Principal of Inherent Holineſs, which the Spirit of Grace (in effectual Calling) hath wrought in thee, (which Inherent Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is (ever) the fruit and effect of a Juſtified State; but never the Procuring (or Meriting) Cauſe. But I account and eſteem thee, as Juſt and Righteous, as if
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102079:12"/> thou hadſt (in thy own Perſon) exactly performed that Legal Righteouſneſs, which the Law Moral requires; on the alone account of my Sons righteouſneſs, which (as the Mediator, and ſurety of this my Covenant of Grace; he is to perform in the behalf of thee, and all mine Elect) I moſt freely impute to thee.</p>
            <p>I Sanctifie, and Renew, thy vitiated, and poluted Nature, by my Sanctifying Spirit, that thou maieſt be capable of Communion and Fellowſhip, with me, both here, in my Church Militant: And here after, in my Church Triumphant.</p>
            <p>I Adopt thee to be my Son, by Grace, and by virtue hereof, thou art reſtored to all the Bleſſings, Rights and Priviledges, which <hi>Adam</hi> (thy Natural and Federal Head) loſt and forfeited, by his Apoſtacy and Defection: Hereby thou art Admitted (as a Free Denizon) into the Family and Houſhold of God: from whence thou waſt caſt out (in <hi>Adam</hi>) when he was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected and caſt out, for his Rebellion, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs his expulſion out of Earthly Paradice a lively Type of the Heavenly. I Promiſe to Eſtabliſh thee in Grace, ſo as thou ſhalt never (more) be in danger, of looſing thy ſelf, or forfeiting my Love and Favour any more: For ever I will be a Sun, and a Shield, to furniſh and ſupply thee with all neceſſary
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102079:12"/> Accomodations for Life in this World; I will Protect and Defend thee, from all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Powers, Spiritually and Bodily, which ſhall contrive and ſeek thy Ruin. And (finally) I will receive thee into Heaven, when (by Death) thou goeſt hence; where thou ſhalt Live and Reign, with me, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.</p>
            <p>And the very ſame Mercy and Favour, which I have (now) expreſſed, and ſhewn to thee; I do oblige my ſelf, by the promiſe of this my Covenant, that I will do to all mine Elect, who are to ſpring from thy Loyns. As alſo, to all mine Elect, who are to come of the Gentile Race; to the end of the World.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Man's Part; As for thee <hi>(Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham)</hi> this thou muſt do, (on thy part) thou muſt walk Humbly and Uprightly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me; thou muſt make the Moral Law (Engraven by the Finger of my Spirit) on the heart of <hi>Adam</hi> (thy Natural and Fede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Head) the ſtanding Rule of thy Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, both Negatively and Poſitively. In all the parts of thy Obedience, thou muſt look (exactly) to three things, (1.) To the Subject Matter of thy Obedience, let it be what I Command and Require, not what Creatures Deviſe or Enjoyn. (2.) To the manner, See that thou do it in Faith, keeping thine Eye on Chriſt (my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102079:13"/> Son) for Acceptance, and Acting all by Strength derived from him. (3.) To the end, See that my Glory be that thou aimeſt at, and deſigneſt, in all thou goeſt about. Thou ſhalt not do my Work and Service in a Mercenary way, as a Servant that Works for Wages; but thou muſt obey my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand as a Son, with freedom of Spirit, and from a Principle of Love and Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, knowing and conſidering, that my Grace and Love hath made Proviſion of all that is needful, to make thee (every way Eternally happy, both here and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. The dreadful Curſe, and Eternal Death, to which (by Sin) thou becameſt obnoxious: My Son Chriſt (Typ'd out by the Ram) hath ſet thee for ever Free from it. And that by his being made a Curſe, and undergoing Death for thee, (as being thy Sponſor or Surety) at his Hands I have Received, the full of that Debt, whereto thou becameſt liable, by breaking my Law, there remains not the leaſt Mite for thee to pay; ſo that (now) thou haſt no cauſe to fear my Vindicative Juſtice; the many and ſharp Afflictions, wherewith thou ſhalt meet, in thy way to Glory, ſhall be but the gentle Chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of thy (dearly) Loving, and Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled Father; who (by them) will Purge out, the remains of thy indwelling Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102079:13"/> and ſweetly wean thee from the enticing Objects of the vain and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching World thou Liveſt in. That Perfect and Spotleſs Righteouſneſs, which muſt Recommend thee to me, and preſent thee Blameleſs, before the Throne of my Glorious Holineſs, in the Third Heaven, is (Subjectively) Inherent, in the Perſon of God-Man, thy Mediator and Surety; to this Mediatorial Righteouſneſs of his, thou ſhalt add nothing, neither thy own Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal qualifications; nor yet, the Holineſs of Saints or Angels; (as if thereby) thou couldeſt be made more Acceptable, than that Righteouſneſs of his doth make thee. Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant, both thou and all thy Eccleſiaſtical, (or Church) Seed, throughout your Generations, till my Son comes to Judge the World at the laſt day. Thou, and all thy Church Seed, (which Springs from thee by Fleſhly Generation,) ſhall obſerve to have all your Males mark'd with Circumciſion, the viſible Token and Seal of this my Gracious Covenant, which I have (now) entred into, with thee; for thy ſelf (a ſtipulating Father,) and for all thy Children; who are to be the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of my Sons Mediatorial Kingdom; or Viſible Church on the Earth.</p>
            <p>And when Chriſt my Son ſhall come in the Fleſh, and ſhall enter upon his Mediatorial
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102079:14"/> Kingdom, whatever viſible Token or Seal he ſhal appoint to Succed in the Room of Circumciſion, thy Gentile Church Seed (as well as Jews,) who are to believe in him, ſhall (carefully) obſerve to be Sealed therewith, both they and their Infants: And that by Virtue of this my Covenant, I now make with thee, for thy ſelf and them. And to the end, that neither thou, nor thy Children (in ſucceeding Ages) may Be Ignorant of what my Will and Pleaſure is, concerning the Non-Elect, who are to come and ſpring from Believing and Holy Parents, in my viſible Church or Churches. I notifie to thee, and thy Church Seed after thee, (throughout their Generations) that my Soveraign Will and Pleaſure is, that all the Infants of my Believing, Profeſſing Church Membrs, ſhall be markt with the Viſible Token or Seal, of this my Covenant in the Church, whereof the Profeſſing Parent (or Parents) are Members, and that without any regard had to the Elect, or Non-Elect. For, ſeeing that the Secrets of my Decrees and Counſels are known to my ſelf alone, I Will, that thou, and thy Church Seed after thee, (to the end of the World) do, in the Judgm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt of (rational) Charity, Judge all the Seed, and Infant Poſterity of my Profeſſing People, who have laid hold on my Covenant, (by an Eternal Viſible
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102079:14"/> Profeſſion) to belong to the Election, and to own them for ſuch, untill they (by open Apoſtacy, and final Impenitency) do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the contrary. For albeit my Viſible Churches do conſiſt of Elect, and Non Elect, and the one as well as the other do partake of the Seal of my Covenant, and are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of all Church Priviledges; yet none ſhall ever partake (internally and ſavingly) of the inward Grace and Mercy Signified, and Sealed by the Token and Seal of my Covenant, (in the Church Viſible,) but the Elect only, whoſe Names are (particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly) Regiſtred in the Lamb's Book of Life. And altho' the Non-Elect in my Church, do fall ſhort of the ſaving Benefits of my Covenant of Grace; yet ſhall they find that I am no way behind with them; for, altho' I (the Abſolute Soveraign of the World) be no way obliged to the Creature (eſpecially fallen Rebels,) yet, ſeeing it is my Pleaſure to Employ the Non-Elect in the Service of my Church, (while it is in a Militant State) that thoſe common Gifts (of my Spirit) wherewith they are to be endowed, might be laid out and improved, for the good and wellfare of my Elect and Choſen; I will give them a Place in my Church, that they ſhall be called by my Name, and ſhall have an equal Right (with mine Elect) to the Seal of my Covenant,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102079:15"/> and all outward helps and means of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the Church Viſible; whereby it ſhall plainly appear (in the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) that their miſſing Heaven, and fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhort of Eternal Life, was of their own Procurement. Notwithſtanding, As is the Service wherein they are Employ'd in my Church, I will give them a plentiful Recompence <hi>(viz.)</hi> a Temperal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in Lieu of a Temporal Service; Such as Bodily Health, Worldly Wealth, Pleaſures and Honours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are (every way) more ſuitable to their Spirit, and are more ſought and delighted in (by them) than are the things laid up for my Choſen: Plain Inſtances (hereof) I have ſeen fit to leave on Record, in the Perſons of <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> both born of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> (according to the Fleſh) the one a Reprobate the other Elect; both muſt be of the Church Viſible, and Sealed with the Viſible Token and Seal of Gods Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with <hi>Abraham.</hi> Of the ſame Nature is that of <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> both born of <hi>Iſaac</hi> (according to Fleſhly Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) yet the one a Reprobate and the other Elect; both muſt be of the Viſible Church, and Sealed with the Seal of the Covenant, and paſs (currant) for Church Members, (before men) untill they (themſelves) make the contrary to appear: As did <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael, Eſau,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102079:15"/>
            <p>And thus, having as plainly and as briefly as I could, (for the information of thoſe who are yet Ignorant of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Covenant) Explained and ſhewn the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and Tenure of Gods Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> for himſelf and all his Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical, or Church Seed, both Jews and Gentiles, to the end of the World.</p>
            <p>I come now to lay down ſome Scriptural Arguments, to Prove, that Gods Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> (as now Explained) is the Covenant of Grace; which God Propounded to <hi>Abraham,</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. And not a Covenant of Works, as the Anabaptiſts Teach it is.</p>
            <p>That it is the Covenant of Grace, and no other, will evidently appear to any, who look not aſquint on the Arguments following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. The firſt Argument is this, If God never yet made a Covenant of Works, with any (mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) Man, but that which he made with ſinleſs <hi>Adam</hi> (the Natural and Federal Head of all Mankind) in the State of Innocency, before the Fall: Then God's Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> is the Covn ant of Grace, and not a Covenant of Works. But God never (yet) made a Covenant of Works, with any meer Man, but that which he made with ſinleſs <hi>Adam,</hi> (the Natural and Federal Head of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind) in the State of Innocency, before
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102079:16"/> the Fall: Therefore, Gods Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. is the Covenant of Grace, and no other. Plain it is, and none (without Lying againſt God) can deny it, that God made a Covenant of Works with <hi>Adam,</hi> and in him with all Mankind.</p>
            <p>The Condition whereof was, do and Live; ſin and Dye. And as plain it is, that <hi>Adam</hi> Fell, by Tranſgreſſing that Covenant, by which Fall he loſt the Bleſſed Image of God to himſelf, and all his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, whereby he and his Poſterity became (utterly uncapable of Life and Salvation by that Covenant.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Abraham</hi> being (by natural Birth) a Son of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and (as ſuch) born under the Curſe of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Covenant, and partaker of a ſinful and polluted Nature; which rendred him as uncapable of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming any Work, which (as a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) can Anſwer the Laws demand; as a man naturally dead, is uncapable of raiſing or quickening himſelf; or as a Sparrow is uncapable to remove, or carry on its Back, the greateſt Mountain in the World. To what end ſhould the only Wiſe God make a Covenant of Works, with ſuch a fallen ſinner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. If to hold and Teach, that God's Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> (in <hi>Gen.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:102079:16"/> 17.7.) is a Covenant of Works, and not a Covenant of Grace, be a high Reflection on God; and alſo deſtructive to the Souls of Men; then is God's Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> (in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7.) the Covenant of Grace, and not a Covenant of Works. But to hold and Teach, that God's Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> (in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7.) is a Covenant of Works, and not a Covenant of Grace, is a High Reflection on God; and deſtructive to the Souls of Men.</p>
            <p>Therefore, God's Covenant with <hi>Abraham, (Gen.</hi> 17.7.) is the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, and not a Covenant of Works.</p>
            <p>For rendring this Argument Unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable, Two things want confirmation. Firſt, That to hold and Teach, that God's Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> is a Covenant of Works, is a high Reflection on God. And Secondly, That the ſame is Deſtructive to the Soules of Men.</p>
            <p>The Firſt of theſe will evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, to the unprejudic'd and Impartial Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if he (ſeriouſly) conſider, how In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent it is, with the Divine Attributes of God, to make a Covenant of Works, with a Lapſed, Polluted Sinner, whom he knows to be (altogether) Dead in Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes and Sins, and (every way) as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to will, or do, any Work that is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102079:17"/> (Spiritually) good, as a Dead Man is able to quicken and raiſe himſelf.</p>
            <p>For Illuſtration ſake, let it be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, How unbecoming a Wiſe and Prudent Man it would be, to ſtrike a Covenant (or Bargain) for ten, or twenty thouſand Pounds, with an Inſolvent Perſon, who is well known not to be worth ten Farthings in the World; and (which is yet worſe) who hath neither Wit to contrive, nor Health or Limbs to Work to get a Penny towards paying ſuch a vaſt Sum. I cannot ſo much as doubt of any (worldly Wiſe) Mans un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs to be guilty of ſuch an overſight as this: And ſhall the (Unerringly) Wiſe God, be guilty of ſo great an Abſurdity?</p>
            <p>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>condly, As this Principle Reflects on God; ſo it is Deſtructive to the Souls of Men. This appears (beyond all contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,) in that it raſeth the very Foundation of Men's Salvation: by denying that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to be a Covenant of Grace, which <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> with <hi>Jacob,</hi> and all the <hi>Old-Teſtament</hi> Believers depended on for Eternal Salvation; and by which, we (Gentile Believers) hope to go to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. For, moſt plain it is, that by this pernicious Principle, <hi>Abraham</hi> is loſt, with all who died truſting to the Grace ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited in that Covenant. And if <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> (the Father of the Faithful) be,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102079:17"/> truſting to a Covenant of Works; I cannot ſee, how any of his Eccelſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Church Seed can be Saved, any more than he is. For, by a Covenant of Works, no meer Man, ever was, or ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll be juſtified and Saved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3 If the Scripture no where, (either directly or by conſequence) calls God's Covenant with <hi>Abraham, (Gen.</hi> 17.7.) a Covenant of Works; then it is a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, and not a Covenant of Works. But the Scripture no where (ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly or by conſequence,) calls God's Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works: Therefore the Covenant of God with <hi>Abraham,</hi> is the Covenant of Grace, and not a Covenant of Works.</p>
            <p>If it cannot be Demonſtrated from the written Word, or by Arguments Deduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble therefrom, that <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. is called, (or can be proved) a Covenant of Works; They who ſo hold and Teach, will be found ranked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe who call good evil; and evil, good; and who put <hi>Light for Darkneſs, and Darkneſs for Light, Eſa.</hi> 5.10. For Men to take on them, to term <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant a Covenant of Works, without any Warrant Divine, is (to me) an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an ignorant, raſh and preſumptuous Spirit: from which Charge, let ſuch Men
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102079:18"/> ſee how they can Acquit and free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. If <hi>Abraham</hi> was Juſtified by Faith, and not by Works; then the Covenant which God made with him, is the Covenant of Grace, and not of Works. But <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was Juſtified by Faith, and not by Works; Therefore the Covenant which God made with him, is the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, and not the Covenant of Works. That <hi>Abraham</hi> was Juſtified by Faith, and not by works, the Scripture is expreſs, and clear, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.2, 3, 4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.5, 6, 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. If God hath made no other Covenant of Grace with <hi>Abraham,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from that in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. then, that Covenant in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. is the Covenant of Grace: but God made no Covenant of Grace, with <hi>Abraham,</hi> diſtinct from that in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. Therefore, that Covenant in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. is the Covenant of Grace, and not the Covenant of Works.</p>
            <p>That which will determin the Point in Controverſie, is this, let thoſe who (herein) oppoſe me, lay down a Scriptural definition of the Covenant of Grace; and that in ſuch Terms, as beſt pleaſe themſelves; and in Caſe, their own definition, do not agree (at leaſt for Subſtance) with <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. if it be according to God's Word, then am I freely
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102079:18"/> willing to own my ſelf (herein) miſtaken: If they refuſe to comply with ſo fair a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, let the Judicious and Impartial Reader Judge, who is at the Loſs (herein,) they or I?</p>
            <p>I conclude this Chapter with this <hi>Dilem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> (viz.) <hi>Abraham,</hi> (the Father of the Faithful) he is e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther Sav'd, or elſe he is Damn'd; one of theſe two the Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries (I now oppoſe) muſt grant, for there is no middle State for Souls Departed.</p>
            <p>If they ſay he is Damn'd, then is there no ground left us to hope, that any of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>'s Poſterity ever were or ſhall be Sav'd; for we have no other Covenant whereby to expect Salvation, but that of <hi>Abraham:</hi> And if he Periſhed under that Covenant, ſo muſt we.</p>
            <p>If they grant, that <hi>Abraham</hi> is in a State of Salvation, (as they muſt, if they ſpeak by the Spirit of Chriſt) then <hi>Abraham</hi> was Juſtified and Saved by a Covenant of Grace, and if by a Covenant of Grace, then that Covenant mention'd in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. muſt needs be the Covenant of Grace; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that Covenant the Scriptures know no other.</p>
            <p>Againſt what I have ſaid, (and all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Proteſtants conſtantly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m) conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ning <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Covenant of pure and abſolute Grace; this is Obj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted by the Adverſaries.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:102079:19"/>
            <p>Object. <hi>The Land of</hi> Canaan <hi>was a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Bleſſing, therefore ſuch was the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, of which Circumciſion was a Tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Seal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer in two Particulars. Firſt, The Promiſe of the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> is no Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial part of the Covenant of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Let the Words in the 7th Verſe be <hi>Read with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice.</hi> The laſt Clauſe of the Verſe doth fully comprehend the ſum and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Covenant of Grace made with <hi>Abraham.</hi> The Promiſe of the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> is only by way of Addition or O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verplus. No Eſſential part of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant it ſelf. The Covenant is briefly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in theſe Words; <hi>I will be a God to thee, and to thy Seed after thee:</hi> For in theſe Words God Engages himſelf (by free and abſolute Promiſe) to <hi>Abraham</hi> and to his Elect Church-Seed, that he will be a God to him and them, to do all things for them, which are needful to compleat their Happineſs, both here and hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, not as it was any Eſſential part of the Covenant of Grace; or, as if real Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs conſiſted in the actual Enjoyment thereof: But as the ſame was a Tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Type of Heaven. And for want of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and conſidering this very thing, many, who have thought themſelves
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102079:19"/> Wiſer (in the Myſteries of the Goſpel) than their Neighbours, have prov'd themſelves ſhort of true Wiſdom; in this Particular at leaſt.</p>
            <p>To convince of this Miſtake, let that of our Saviour (in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. <hi>But ſeek ye firſt the kingdom of God, and the righteouſneſs there of, and all theſe things ſhall be added to you</hi>) be weighed in the Ballance of an unprejudiced Conſideration; and to an Impartial Eye, that looks not Aſquint at theſe two places of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. it will moſt plainly appear, that Temporal Bleſſings are held forth in one, as well as in the other. And if it muſt needs be granted, that becauſe God made the Promiſe of the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> to <hi>Abraham,</hi> &amp;c. that therefore God's Covenant with him and his, was a Covenant of Works: It will (as neceſſarily follow, that Believers to whom Chriſt directs his Speech in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. are now under a Covenant of Works, as well as <hi>Abraham</hi> was. And ſo, neither <hi>Abraham</hi> (the Father of the Faithful) nor any of his Seed, (the Elect I mean) either of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> or <hi>Gentile</hi> Race, are like to be Saved or Enjoy God for their Portion. And by this way of Arguing, it will evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appear to any ſeeing Man, (who ſhuts not his Eyes for fear of being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced) that while the Adverſaries (I now
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102079:20"/> Oppoſe in this Controverſy) were employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in deviſing this Shift to prove God's Covenant (with <hi>Abraham</hi>) to be a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works; and that (on purpoſe) to exclude poor Infants from that Covenant, and from Baptiſm (the now Seal thereof,) they have (inſenſibly) ſhut both <hi>Abraham</hi> and themſelves too, out from being Saved: And what advantage will (hereby) accrew to their Cauſe, let it be improved to the utmoſt.</p>
            <p>Object. 2. <hi>It is again Objected, If the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in</hi> Gen. 17.7. <hi>be a Covenant of pure Grace, and not a Covenant of Works, and that all</hi> Abraham<hi>'s Children be alike Intereſted therein, then doth Grace come by natural Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, contrary both to Scripture and Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ground of the Objectors mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, Lyes in two things: Firſt, His not diſtinguiſhing or conſidering, that the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Believing <hi>Abraham,</hi> are ſaid to be in Covenant two Ways, or in a twofold Reſpect: Firſt, Internally, by Virtue of God's Election: And thus none are (or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall be) in Covenant, but <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, <hi>(viz)</hi> The Elect, who are in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (by way of diſtinction) ſtyled, the Children of Promiſe, Typ'd out in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Jſaac, Gal.</hi> 4 28.</p>
            <p>Theſe (and they alone) Partake in the ſaving benefits of the Covenant; and have
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102079:20"/> alſo a right to the viſible Sign or Seal of the Covenant in the viſible Churches of Chriſt, under the Goſpel Diſpenſation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Externally, by Virtue of the External Profeſſion made in the Church: And thus the Non-Elect (as well as the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect) are ſaid to be in Covenant with God, in his Churches Viſible, (here on Earth.) Theſe Albeit, they never partake in the ſaving Bleſſings of the Covenant; yet by Virtue of the External Profeſſion made, they and their Infant-Seed, (though not Elect,) have an External Right (in the Church Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) to the Token (or Seal) of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant; and to all other Priviledges and Ordinances in the Church, whereof they are capable, according to the Revealed Will of God: By Virtue hereof it is, that God calls ſuch his People; and he will have his Church to call and own them for ſuch too, until they manifeſt themſelves to be otherwiſe; and that by a voluntary Defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and final Apoſtacy. Plain Inſtances hereof are (Graphically) ſet down in God's Word, in the Perſons of <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> (in whoſe Perſons the Reprobate Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> were (Allegorically) typ'd out as the Elect Seed) were Allegorically and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pically repreſented in the Perſons of <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob:</hi> The former of theſe Sprang from the Fleſh of <hi>Abraham,</hi> as well as the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102079:21"/> latter: And on this account, they had a place in the Viſible Church, and were mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Seal of God's Covenant, as well as the latter. They were eſteemed and reckoned as God's Children, and true Members of the Church, until (by Defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Apoſtacy) they diſcovered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be otherwiſe. If this Diſtinction be not allowed, I cannot ſee how God can be (orderly) Worſhip't by any Viſible Church on Earth.</p>
            <p>This is the Summ and Subſtance of God's Covenant, made with <hi>Abraham</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. and with his Elect Seed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And by Virtue of this Promiſe, <hi>Abraham</hi> and (with him) all his Elect Seed would have been moſt Happy and eternally Bleſt, had no Promiſe been made of the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> So (in like manner) ſhall all true Believers (with their Elect Seed, be eternally Happy and Bleſt, being made Partakers of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, (intended in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33.) Albeit ſuch Believers (and their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Seed) ſhould (with <hi>Lazarus</hi>) Die on a Dunghil, for want of thoſe Temporal Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings held forth by Chriſt, in the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Promiſe, which plainly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, that the Promiſe which God made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> of giving to him and to his Seed, the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> was no more an Eſſential part of the Covenant made
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102079:21"/> with him and his Seed, than the Promiſe held forth by Chriſt, in the place (above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named) proves, that Believers and their Elect Seed are (now) under a Covenant of Works. All the difference which I can find between theſe two places, is, that the Promiſe in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. was Typical of the Kingdom of Heaven: The other is not ſo. Were this Covenant of God made with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> (the Father of the Faithful) as he was a Stipulating and a Covenanting Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative (in a Church Viſible,) but rightly underſtood and believ'd with Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to Mens own Souls, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded there would be neither Anabaptiſts nor Arminian in the World.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> Holds and Teaches that Ignorance is the Mother of Devotion: I am not aſhamed to ſay, it is the Mother of all Errors in Religion. Neither am I afraid to affirm it to be both the Mother and Nurſe of Anabaptiſm and Arminia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Proving that Circumciſion was a Seal of Gods Covenant of Grace, made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Seed.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. EIther Circumciſion was the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Token (or Seal) of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102079:22"/> Covenant (of Grace) mentioned, <hi>G.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 7. Or elſe that Covenant had no Seal at all</p>
            <p>The Adverſary cannot avoid here, H muſt either Grant or Deny; if he gran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that Circumciſion was the Seal of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Covenant, I have what I was to prove; if he deny it to be the Seal of that Covenant, then it lyes at his Door to demonſtrate what was the Seal of that Covenant: If he ſay that that Covenant had no Seal at all, He will (thereby) not only gainſay the Word of God, but alſo ſpeak againſt reaſon; for all Men know it is an eſſential property of a Covenant to have a Seal, to confirm the matter contained in the Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> (2.) If Circumciſion is (by God himſelf) called the Seal of the Covenant, then is it (beyond all Controverſy) the Seal of the Covenant.</p>
            <p>But Circumciſion is (by God himſelf) cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Seal of the Covenant.</p>
            <p>Therefore Circumciſion is (beyond all controverſy) the Seal of the Covenant. For Proof of the Argument, compare <hi>Acts</hi> 7, 8, with <hi>Gen.</hi> 17, 10. To which I will only add, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4, 11, which will put the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (in Diſpute) beyond the reach of all Diſpute. The Words are plain and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, in calling Circumciſion the Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith; which plainly proves two things. Firſt, That Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102079:22"/> is a Seal of the Covenant made with <hi>Abraham.</hi> Secondly, That the Covenant of which Circumciſion was the Seal, was the Covenant of Grace, and no other.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>That Water-Baptiſm ſucceeded, or came in the room of Circumciſion, (under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Diſpenſation) I prove by <hi>3</hi> convincing Arguments.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. IF there be no other Initiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Seal appointed by Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder the Goſpel but Water-Baptiſm, then is Water-Baptiſm come (or ſuceeeded) in the room of Circumciſion, to be the initia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Seal under the Goſpel: But there is no other initiatory Seal appointed by Chriſt under the Goſpel, but Water-Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>Therefore Water-Baptiſm is come or ſucceeded in the room of Circumciſion, to be the initiatory Seal under the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The truth and ſtrength of this Argument will the more clearly appear, by duly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that Circumciſion was (under the dark Diſpenſation of the Law) the initia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Seal of the Covenant, which will not, (cannot) be denyed, unleſs by Men who underſtand (or care) not what they ſay: That Water-Baptiſm is, (and muſt be) ſo
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102079:23"/> now; muſt (of neceſſity) be acknowledged by all who own that the Lords Supper ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, or came in the room of the Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>I humbly conceive no Wiſe Man will op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe me, in ſaying that the Churches of the New-Teſtament have as great need of an initiating Seal of the Covenant of Grace, as had the Church of the Jews under the Old: And if Baptiſm be not that Seal, I know not what is; for that Circumciſion is (now) abrogated and aboliſhed under the Goſpel, none can deny; and that ſome other viſible ſign muſt ſucceed (or come) in its room, muſt be granted by them who acknowledge that the Lords Supper ſucceeded (or came) in the room of the Paſſeover.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> (2.) If the Adverſaries themſelves do (practically) own Baptiſm to be the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiating Seal of the Goſpel Covenant, then Baptiſm is the initiating Seal of the Goſpel Covenant: But the Adverſaries themſelves do (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ractically) own Baptiſm to be the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiating Seal of the Goſpel Covenant. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Baptiſm is the initiating Seal of the Goſpel Covenant.</p>
            <p>Thoſe I (here) diſpute againſt, before they can overthrow this Argument, muſt abandon their own practice in making Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm by Dipping, the Door of Entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Churches; by which Practice they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102079:23"/> Unchurch all other Churches who are not of their own Perſwaſion. It is well known in <hi>London,</hi> and elſe where, where Anabaptiſm is practiſed, that they make Baptiſm (by Dipping) the form of a right Goſpel Church; on which account it is they refuſe Communion (in the Lords Supper) with the moſt Sanctified Believers, if they are not Dipt after their Mode.</p>
            <p>'Tis true that ſome of that Perſwaſion would ſeem more moderate and charitable than others (of that way) while they make Saintſhip the (only) term of Church Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: Theſe ſeem not to lay ſuch ſtreſs on Baptiſm as the reſt of that Perſwaſion do; they will admit to the Lords Supper (with them) thoſe of other Perſwaſions, though not Baptized in their way; but how ſuch will be able to juſtify their practice in admitting Unbaptized Perſons to the Lords Supper, I cannot underſtand; to me it is plain, that there is the ſame parity of reaſon for keeping back an Unbaptized Perſon from the Lords Table, as there was for keeping back an Uncircumciſed Perſon from the Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over of Old. The firſt of theſe <hi>(viz.)</hi> Baptiſm is the viſible Badge of our Union (with Chriſt) in Regeneration, (as Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was to the Believing Jews) The other, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Lords Supper, is the viſible Badge of our Communion and Fellowſhip with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102079:24"/> Chriſt, as the Paſſover (of Old) was to the Believing Circumciſed Jews: Now, as Communion is a fruit of Union, and follows after it, ſo no Perſon ought to be admitted to the ſecond, that is, not (actually) a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Partaker of the firſt. It is not to be doubted, that theſe who (in Charity) invite us to the Lords Table (with them) do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count us as Unbaptized Perſons, while they reckon our Baptiſm (received in Infancy, and by Sprinkling) but a meer nullity, that is, no Baptiſm at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. If Water Baptiſm have the ſame end and uſe aſſigned it by God, as Circumciſion had of old, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to ſignifie and Seal to Believers and their Infants E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, the truth of their Regeneration, <hi>&amp;c</hi> Then Water Baptiſm hath Succeeded in the room of Circumciſion. But Water Baptiſm hath the ſame end and uſe Aſſign'd it by God, as Circumciſion had of old, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to ſignifie, and Seal to Believers (and their Elect Infants,) the truth of their Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore, Water Baptiſm hath Succeeded, in the room of Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>This Argument depends on the Right and Genuine Explication, of that Text, in <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.11. <hi>In whom alſo ye are Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, with the Circumciſion made without Hands; in puting off the Body of the ſins of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102079:24"/> the Fleſh, by the Circumciſion of Chriſt,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Buried with him in Baptiſm, wherein alſo, you are Riſen with him, through the Faith of the Operation of God, who hath raiſed him from the Dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not here meddle with Explaining this, becauſe, I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak to it when I come to Anſwer the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons brought againſt Baptiſm being come in the room of Circumciſion: whereto I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer my Reader.</p>
            <p>Againſt what hath been ſaid, concerning Circumciſion being the Seal of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it is Objected, thus,</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Circumciſion was only a Seal of a Temporal, Carnal Covenant, Sealing only Earthly and Temporal Bleſſings, to the Carnal Church of the Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this Objection, I Anſwer in three Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I have already proved, that God's Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> of which Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was the Seal) was (and ſtill is) the Covenant of Grace, and not a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Works; as ſome Ignorant and Injudicious Teachers would fain have it to be: And that (meerly) on the account of keeping Poor Infants from Baptiſm, which they know could never be Juſtified, (by God's Word) ſhould they Judiciouſly acknowledge, that <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102079:25"/> is the Covenant of Grace; and that Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, was the Seal thereof: and that Water Baptiſm, is (now) come in the room thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In that ſome have reflected on that Covenant, calling it a carnal Covenant of Works, and the Church which was to Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and Practice Circumciſion (the Seal thereof) a carnal Church: all I need to ſay (by way of Reply) is, to bewail the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallity of their Uncircumciſed Hearts and Lips; who have no better or higher Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of God's Holy Covenant, (the Grace whereof muſt bring them to Heaven if ever they come thither,) and of his ſo highly Honoured Friends, <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> with all the reſt of the Holy Patriarchs, Prophets and Godly Believers of that Day; than to call it a carnal Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and them a carnal Church.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant, was a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Works, to him and his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, then it muſt (needs) he ſo to us Gentile Believers, and to our Children now.</p>
            <p>And if ſo, let the Adverſary De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate (if he can) how <hi>Abraham,</hi> or any of that carnal Church (as they falſely term it) can be ſuppoſed, to be (now) in a Saved State: Or, what ground of hope, we Gentile Believers (and our Children)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:102079:25"/> have, that we or any of ours ſhall go to Heaven when we Die, ſeeing that we are ſtill under the very ſame Covenant with <hi>Abraham;</hi> which Covenant, if it be a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Works, and not of Grace, no Salvation, can be expected; and if the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers (under that dark Diſpenſation) were Carnal, and not Spiritual, how comes the unerring Wiſdom of God to Propound them to Believers under the Goſpel, for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples and Patterns of Faith, Patience, <hi>&amp;c. Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Ja.</hi> 5.10. Let it be farther conſidered, that, Albeit, the Seal of Circumciſion Sealed no ſaving Bleſſings to the Non-Elect; it doth not hence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that it Sealed no other than Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Bleſſings to the Elect, ſeeing, that (to them) the Heavenly were (Typically) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the Earthly.</p>
            <p>As touching the Earthly Bleſſings, which Circumciſion Sealed to the Non-Elect, they were greater and better than God was (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way) obliged to give them. I am ſure than they (ſavingly) improved.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>We utterly deny, that Water-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm did ſucceed and come in the room of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For confirmation of the Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, let the three Arguments already laid down under this Head be ſeriouſly (and without prejudice) conſidered: To which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102079:26"/> I will only add the Explication of <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.11, 12. whereon I have grounded a fourth Argument, to prove, that Water-Baptiſm ſucceeded and came in the room of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion. In the place above quoted, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle plainly ſets forth to the believing <hi>Coloſſians</hi> (and in them to all believing <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> to the Worlds end) two things, (ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be known and believed by all true Believers.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That they, who (by a true lively Faith) have Embrac'd the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, (as held forth in the Goſpel,) evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencing their Faith by the Truth of Goſpel-Sanctification. They (and none elſe) who are Adult, are made actual Partakers of the true and ſaving Circumciſion, effected in the Soul by the Spirit of Chriſt. And which was (Externally) ſignified by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Circumciſion.</p>
            <p>Theſe Believers having (now) obtained the Spiritual Circumciſion, are not at all to be Concerned or Troubled, that they are not outwardly Circumciſed with the Circumciſion made with Man's Hands. Foraſmuch as that which was (Externally) Signified and Sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to the believing <hi>Jews,</hi> by the outward Circumciſion, is (now In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally and Powerfully) wrought in their Hearts by the Spirit of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:102079:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Apoſtle ſets forth in this place, that Water-Baptiſm is Inſtituted and Appointed by Chriſt (under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Diſpenſation) to be (to believing <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi>) the ſame that Circumciſion was to the <hi>Jews, (viz.)</hi> A Viſible Sign and Seal of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant to all his Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Church-Seed among the <hi>Gentiles, (viz.)</hi> All of that Race, who (on God's calling them) Believe in and Obey the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. To theſe and their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Seed (and none elſe among the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi>) Baptiſm doth (now under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel) Signify and Seal the very ſame Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Bleſſings and Church-Priviledges, which Circumciſion (of old) did Signify and Seal to the believing <hi>Jews</hi> and their Infant-Seed.</p>
            <p>This I take to be the Senſe and Meaning of the Apoſtle, in that ſo much controvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed place. In this Senſe, I hope, I ſhall Die ſatisfied. And herein (I humbly conceive) none of the Orthodox will differ from me, which Senſe being granted, it is beyond the reach of all Scriptural contradiction, that Water-Baptiſm was Inſtituted and Appointed (by Chriſt) on purpoſe to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the room of Circumciſion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:102079:27"/>
            <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Shewing and proving, that the Infants of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Gentiles</hi> (now under the Goſpel) have as real a Right to the Covenant of Grace, and to Baptiſm, the (now) Viſible Sign and Seal thereof; as had the Children of <hi>Abraham</hi> (according to the Fleſh) to it, and to Circumciſion, the then Seal of the Covenant of Grace.</p>
               <p>And, that they are as capable of the Grace and outward Seal of the Covenant, as are the moſt Adult grown Believers.</p>
               <p>I ſhall lay down Four Arguments, to evince and make good (againſt all Oppoſition) what I now aſſert.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. THE firſt Argument is thus fram'd: If God (himſelf) did, by abſolute Soveraign Grace, comprehend <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Church-Seed in the Covenant of Grace he made with believing <hi>Abraham,</hi> (their Stipulating and Covenanting Father) and never ſince Repeal'd that Gracious Act of his: Then the Infants of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Church-Seed are ſtill Intereſted in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, and have as great Right to, and are as capable of the Grace and Seal of that Covenant as ever.</p>
            <p>But God (himſelf) did by abſolute So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Grace, comprehend <hi>Abraham</hi>'s
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102079:27"/> Church-Seed in the Covenant of Grace he made with believing <hi>Abraham,</hi> (their Stipulating and Covenanting Father) which Gracious Act of his was never ſince Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Infants of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Church-Seed are ſtill Intereſſed in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, and have as great a Right to, and are as capable of the Grace and Seal of that Covenant as ever.</p>
            <p>I cannot ſee how this Argument can (poſſibly) be overthrown, but by proving, that God did alter and change that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant he made with <hi>Abraham</hi> (his Friend,) for himſelf and for his Church-Seed: The which, when the Adverſary doth by Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Scripture, (not abuſed and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted,) I ſhall then yield the Cauſe, and bewail my Miſtake. But two things cauſe in me an unſhaken Confidence, that this can never be done. <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Immutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Unchangableneſs of God, on which very account he is ſtyled a Covenant-keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, who never yet caſt off any poor Sinner, until that Sinner did firſt actually caſt God off; the which (I think) the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary dares not deny. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Impoſſibility of poor Infants actually caſting God off, and that becauſe of their Incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city in reſpect of Age.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:102079:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. If Infants be at all Saved, they are Saved by the Grace of God's Covenant made with <hi>Abraham;</hi> which Covenant, and the External Seal thereof, (in the Viſible Church) muſt belong to them alſo.</p>
            <p>But Infants are Saved by the Grace of God's Covenant, (made with <hi>Abraham</hi>) and in no other way.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Covenant of God's Grace (by which they are Saved) and the Seal thereof, (in the Viſible Church) muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to them alſo.</p>
            <p>This Argument hath been conſtantly maintained (by the Orthodox) againſt the Enemies of Infant-Baptiſm, with ſuch ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, that I never yet heard the Man's Name, who was able to anſwer or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the ſame by ſound or ſolid Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>To deny Salvation to Infants is a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple ſo monſtrouſly Cruel and Uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, (expoſing to the Judgment of God, and to the deſerved Frowns of all Tender-hearted Parents) that ſome, who account it a point of great Skill and Wiſdom, (in the Myſtery of the Goſpel) to Decry and Witneſs againſt Infant-Baptiſm, have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared themſelves ſtrongly inclin'd to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that all Infants are Saved, and that without diſtinguiſhing between Elect and Reprobate, or between the Seed of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:102079:28"/> Godly Believers, and that of Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a Principle (altogether) as ſilly and groundleſs as that of denying the Right of Believers Infant-Seed to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, and the Viſible Token or Seal thereof in the Church. And at what Door this (Heterodox) Dream ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or from what Root or Principle it ſhould ſpring, I know not, unleſs from that Popiſh Arminian Principle of general Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and univerſal Grace. Here, by the Conceſſion (or Grant) of the very Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, Infants are Saved; but how, or in what way? whether by a Covenant or without a Covenant. Here they are (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly) ſilent, not daring to mention any Covenant at all, fearing an Advantage may be (thereby) given, to diſcover or prove the Right of Infants to the Covenant. It is ſufficient (ſuch Dreamers Judge) to leave poor Infants to the general Mercy and Grace of God, as thoſe do, who Dream and Conceit, that the very Damned in Hell ſhall (at length) be delivered from the Torments of that Place. For which Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical Whym, there is as much to be ſaid (from the Word of God.) As there is to prove, that God will extend the Grace of his Covenant to all Infants Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:102079:29"/>
            <p>The Adverſary (I diſpute againſt) knows (very well,) that ſhould it be granted <hi>(in Terminis)</hi> in plain Terms, that Infants are Saved by the Grace of the Covenant, it can no way be avoided, but that Infants muſt be in that Covenant, and muſt have an Indiſputable Right <hi>(in foro Eccleſiae)</hi> to the outward Seal thereof.</p>
            <p>But this muſt be deny'd, and its contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry aſſerted, (for the moſt Glorious Goſpel-Truth,) <hi>(viz.)</hi> That Believers only (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding their Infants) are Intereſted in the Covenant, and have a Right to the Seal thereof; and that in the Right of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion they make before Men.</p>
            <p>Now, how abſurd and contrary to the very Tenure and Deſign of God's Covenant with Chriſt (in the behalf of the Elect) this Principle of Anabaptiſm is? I leave to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Unprejudiced Reader (who underſtands any thing in Religion) to Judge. And whether to reſtrain the Promiſe of God's Covenant (which equally extends to all the Elect) to that part of the Elect, which are Adult and Grown up, to make a Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to extend the Grace of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bounds of his own Covenant, be not equally to Raſe the Foundation of Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Truth, and to Uſurp the Throne of God (or to Invade his Prerogative) in the Church; I leave to Wiſe Men to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:102079:29"/>
            <p>If thus to do falls not under that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Commination (or Woe threatned) in <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18. I am greatly miſtaken.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. If Infants do ſtand in as real need of the Grace of God's Covenant as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dult do, and be (every way) as capable thereof as the Adult are, then muſt they (of neceſſity) be allow'd the Seal thereof in the Church.</p>
            <p>But Infants do ſtand in as real need of the Grace of God's Covenant, and are (every way) as capable thereof as the Adult are.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Seal of God's Covenant in the Church muſt (of neceſſity) be allow'd them.</p>
            <p>That Infants are Partakers of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Guilt, and alſo of that Pravity and Pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Nature, which came by <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall, I am confident will be deny'd by none (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs by downright Dreamers) now to own this.</p>
            <p>And at the ſame time to Teach and Hold, that Infants are (becauſe not Grown up to the uſe of Reaſon and actual Faith) unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Regeneration, is to deny Salvation to all Infants, who Die Infants: And how well this Principle accords with all Infants being Saved, (who Die Infants) is not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to underſtand. If this be not <hi>Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictio in Terminis, (viz.)</hi> A Contradiction in plain Terms, I know not what a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction means.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:102079:30"/>
            <p>The Lord Chriſt (who can neither lye nor be deceived in what he ſaith) aſſures us, that <hi>except one be Born again, he cannot (poſſibly) ſee the Kingdom of God. Jo.</hi> 3.8. wherein the abſolute need of Regeneration is diſcovered and aſſerted; and the Subject of which, this is predicated (in that Text) being indefinitely and univerſally expreſt; we are taught that neither Adult nor Infant, ſhall ever enter Heaven, till that work of Regeneration paſs on the guilty polluted Soul: And to ſay that an Adult (or grown) Perſon (by reaſon of his Age) is capable of this great Change, but that an Infant (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he wants the uſe of reaſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) is uncapable of it. What is this but (inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretatively) to hold and ſay that the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures own will and reaſon muſt concurr to the producing the New Creature in a Dead Soul.</p>
            <p>And how advantageous this Principle is to <hi>Papiſts, Arminians, Pelagians</hi> and <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians;</hi> the Learned and Orthodox well know.</p>
            <p>The Enemies themſelves do (with us) acknowledge that Water-Baptiſm is a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Ordinance; and ſtrange it is, that thoſe (of that Party) who are concerned to deck and adorn the Frontiſpiece of their Books (againſt Infant-Baptiſm) with ſuch Ornate Floriſhes of Greek, Hebrew, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:102079:30"/> Latin Sentences, do not (in their way of arguing about this matter) give us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that they underſtand and know the meaning and proper ſignification of the word Paſſive, better than it appears they do; certain it is, and the Learned know it) that the term Paſſive ſignifies and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports a Non-agency in the Subject, when a change is paſſing on it, or a work producing in it; to the effecting of which change (or work) the Subject Recipient neither wills nor acts any thing towards the producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch a change.</p>
            <p>If I underſtand any thing of Gods Mind (revealed in the Sacred Scripture) or was ever (experimentally) acquainted with the Spirits method in paſſing that great change on a Sinner, in effectual Calling. The work conſiſts of two parts. Firſt, Gods Gracious Acts, in freely Pardoning all the Rebels Sins and Tranſgreſſions committed againſt the Law, imputing to him that ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Righteouſneſs of Chriſt his Son (the Sinners Sponſor or Surety) as truly and really as if that ſpotleſs Righteouſneſs had been acted performed by the Sinner himſelf (Perſonally.) This is the firſt part wherein that great change lyes or conſiſts, which (in Divinity) is called Juſtification.</p>
            <p>The Second is, Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s quickening and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing the inward Powers and Faculties of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:102079:31"/> the Soul, by communicating a principle of Spiritual Life to the Sinner, in every of the Souls faculties within: I do not mean (or intend) that in this work of Regenerating the Sinner, the Natural faculties (concrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Nature of <hi>Adam</hi>) are deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or annihilated, but that the Predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy of thoſe vitious qualities (inhering in the Souls faculties) is overpowered by the Sanctification of the Spirit; and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Principle of ſaving (and unlooſable) Grace is communicated to every of theſe faculties in the Soul, whereby the new Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple communicated, maintains its own Being in thoſe reſpective Faculties, (and this through the continual ſupply of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which produced the change) and making continual reſiſtance againſt that Vice and Corruption (as yet) remaining in the ſame Faculties where the new Creature is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to War and Combat, until that Sinleſs Perfection (promiſed in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace) ſuperſede and diſpoſſeſs that indwelling Corruption (in the Soul) under which the new Creature continues to groan, until a perfect releaſe come.</p>
            <p>This is called Sanctification; and when the ſet time (prefixt in Gods Decree) for calling an Elect Sinner, is come; what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth this great change?</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:102079:31"/>
            <p>I will ſuppoſe the Sinner to be come to the Years of Manhood, capable of acting or exerciſing his natural Faculties; doth his will or his reaſon help the Almighty in producing ſo miraculous a change? can the Eye of this Sinners blind reaſon (and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding) ſee into or comprehend the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Myſtery of that Wiſdom manifeſted and ſet forth in that ſtupendious and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing contrivance of Gods juſtifying and reconciling to himſelf an Apoſtate, Rebel, Sinner, by the imputed Righteouſneſs of another? can the Eye of blind reaſon be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of this? can the Will of this dead Sinner incline or move it ſelf towards the Sinners own Converſion, to be a Coadjutor or Fellow-helper, to forward or help the Almighty in effecting this ſtrange and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous change? can it (poſſibly) be that Spiritual (or Corporal) Blindneſs can cure it ſelf, or that Enmity and Rebellion can change its own Nature?</p>
            <p>Let the experience of every (rightly) aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured Believer ſpeak to this.</p>
            <p>If then nothing in the poor dead Sinner, neither the uſe of his natural reaſon, nor yet any activity in his unrenewed Will doth contribute any help to produce ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a change; the work muſt needs be (en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely) Gods own work. From which I ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue in the behalf of poor Infants, if God
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102079:32"/> can, and doth freely pardon and blot out the Millions of actual Sins (added to the original guilt) of an adult Sinner; if he can and doth freely and moſt graciouſly impute the Righteouſneſs of his Son; and by thus doing, juſtifies an adult Sinner: If God can (and doth) by the irreſiſtable efficacy of his own Holy Spirit, renew the faculties of the Soul of an adult Sinner, which is (as I may ſay) ſteeped (and even ſoaked) in Vitioſity and actual Pollution; cannot the ſame Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, Juſt, Wiſe and Gracious God do and effect the like change in and upon a poor helpleſs Infant, though that Infant underſtand not what is done to it, neither is capable of contributing any help towards ſo great a change?</p>
            <p>From what hath been (here) offered to conſideration, to me it is evident and plain, that when Men cry out and ſay, Infants, (while Infants) are uncapable of Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe they want the uſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they ſpeak moſt injuriouſly and ignorantly againſt God himſelf, as if he could not (or would not) effect that in and for an Elect Infant which he doth for an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dult Sinner; as the juſtifying and renewing an adult Sinner hath no dependence on the reaſon, will or ſpeech of a grown Sinner, even ſo the want of actual reaſon, activity of Will or Speech in an Infant, cannot (poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly)
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102079:32"/> hinder God from effecting this great and gracious work in and upon an Elect In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, though the poor Infant can do nothing towards ſo great a change. The Subject Recipient of this work of Regeneration, is (every way) Paſſive, the adult as well as the Infant.</p>
            <p>Agreeable to this Act of Gods in chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Sinner, is that Ordinance of Water-Baptiſm, whoſe principal uſe is twofold. Firſt, to ſignifie and repreſent his own gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious dealing with the Sinner (Baptized) in Pardoning all his Sins, for Chriſts ſake; whoſe Blood repreſented by the Water in Baptiſm) was ſhed for the Remiſſion of the Sins of all, comprehended in that Covenant of Grace, whereof Baptiſm is a Seal. And Secondly, that it may be a Seal to confirm to the Baptized (if Elect) all the gracious Promiſes of the ſame Covenant of Grace; as Gods work (upon the Soul of a true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert) is (in reſpect of the Sinner) wholly Paſſive, ſo Baptiſm (the outward Sign and Seal of Gods Covenant of Grace) is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Paſſive: And as the Wiſdom of Chriſt ſaw fit to appoint the Element of material Water to be uſed in Baptiſm, as (above all the other Elements) moſt ſuited to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of that Ordinance, becauſe of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie and reſemblance which is between Water and the Blood of Chriſt; ſo no
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:102079:33"/> mode or way of adminiſtring this Water-Baptiſm doth ſo exactly and to the life, ſet forth the freeneſs of Gods Grace and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy (exhibited) in the Covenant of Grace, then the act of Sprinkling or pouring out the Water on the Party Baptized. By this way of Sprinkling (under the Goſpel) there is a ſweet and orderly Harmony kept be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Pen-men of Gods Word, both under the Old and New-Teſtament Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, with whom, whoever ſtudys to agree (in applying the Water of Holy Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm) they will be (at length) found to be in the right; how many and black Cenſures ſoever are heapt on them by injudicious Spirits: The Spirit of God (in the work of Regeneration) applys the Spiritual Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm by Sprinkling or pouring out of his Graces on the Soul. There muſt be an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogie kept between the thing ſignified and the outward Sign.</p>
            <p>Againſt what hath been laid down to prove Infants right to Baptiſm, (the Seal of Gods Covenant) many things are object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I will (for brevity ſake) contract the Objections (with my Anſwers) to as few particulars as (poſſibly) I can.</p>
            <p>Object. 1. <hi>In the Words of the Grand Commiſſion, there is not one word concerning Infants.</hi> Mat. 28.19. Go ye and Teach all Nations, Baptizing them in the Name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:102079:33"/>
            <p>This ſeems too weak, (though well mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) Minds to be unanſwerable: But in the ſtrength of him who gave out this Grand Commiſſion, I hope to ſhew how wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Objector is miſtaken herein.</p>
            <p>In order whereto, let two things be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly (and warily) conſidered.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that albeit Chriſt the Lord doth not mention Infants (in particular) yet he includes them in the Words of the general Commiſſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Go Teach all Nations, Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them,</hi> &amp;c. Here the Lord commands (expreſly) that all ſuch as belong to Gods Covenant (with <hi>Abraham) Gen.</hi> 7.7. ſhall be Baptized; Namely, all who ſhall embrace the Son of God by Faith, and their Infant-Seed (if any they have) That this is the true ſenſe and meaning of Chriſt in that place, is clear to any who do not (wilfully) ſhut their Eyes; for evident it is, and none can deny that he (there) commands to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize all Nations, not excepting againſt or forbidding the Diſciples to Baptize little Infants: He knew that he ſpake to Men, who (after the ſending of the Holy Ghoſt) ſhould know and conſider that <hi>Abrahams</hi> Covenant (with Believers and their Infant-Seed) was to remain and continue the ſame to the end of the World. And this, (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the ſharp rebuke he gave to his Apoſtles, for offering to hinder Little Ones
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:102079:34"/> being brought to him; and his laying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them ſuch a convincing reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch ſhould not be kept from coming to him. <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.14. was the principal, (if not the only reaſon) wherefore his infinite Wiſdom ſaw it not needful to mention In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants in particular, they being (moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly) included in the general term all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: All Men (who know any thing of Learning) underſtand that <hi>Omne majus continet in ſe minus,</hi> (every greater includes (or contains in it the leſſer) is a ſure and ſtanding Rule both in Logick and Divinity.</p>
            <p>Agreeing with this ſenſe (I have given off the Grand Commiſſion) is that of <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 2.39. <hi>For the Promiſe is to you and to your Children,</hi> &amp;c. which affords an invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Argument to prove that there is (now under the Goſpel) no change of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Covenant, (any other than in the external adminiſtration of it) The Covenant (in its ſubſtance) abides the ſame for ever: By the Grace thereof all Gods Elect (both of the Jewiſh and Gentile Race) are to be Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.29. What I have ſaid will yet receive farther confirmation by what is laid down by <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. <hi>That the Bleſſing of</hi> Abraham <hi>might come upon the Gentiles, through Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. The places now quoted out of <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. preſuppoſe a command to all,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:102079:34"/> (whether Jew or Gentile) who (by Faith) receives Jeſus Chriſt for a Saviour) that they ſhall be Signed with the Seal of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> Covenant, according to <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.9. For if the Gentiles (who believe in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> Saviour) do expect that they and their Infants ſhould be made actual Partakers of the Bleſſings of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Covenant; they muſt be ſure to obſerve and keep Gods Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with <hi>Abraham</hi> throughout their Generations.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſeeing that Chriſt (himſelf) words the Commiſſion ſo in general terms, (which (undoubtedly) includes the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular) not excepting againſt Infants: It muſt (neceſſarily) follow, that if Infants be a part of thoſe Nations which the Apoſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are commanded to Baptize; that Chriſt commands them to Baptize Infants as well as any others. Reader, obſerve the Words of the Commiſſion, <hi>Go and Teach all Nations,</hi> &amp;c. Here is no more mention of grown Perſons, Men or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, than there is of Infants. If then A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts cannot deny that Infants are a part of Nations, and that they can no way prove how <hi>Abrahams</hi> Bleſſing can come on the Gentiles (through Chriſt Jeſus) any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way than by and through the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of <hi>Abraham.</hi> It will (unavoidably) follow, (all the Wit in Man cannot oppoſe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:102079:35"/> it with ſucceſs) that Infants as well as adult Perſons are (as the proper Subjects of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm) intended (by Chriſt) in the Grand Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>Object. 2. <hi>None are the proper Subjects of Baptiſm, but ſuch as are firſt taught</hi> Go and Teach, <hi>&amp;c. Infants are not capable of Mans Teaching, therefore they are not the proper Subjects of Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This, with the Objection already ſpoken to, ſeems (to weak and injudicious People) to be unanſwerable, (for excluding Infants from Baptiſm) but he that looks into it with a Spiritual Eye, will find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it againſt Infants.</p>
            <p>In order to diſcover the weakneſs and miſtake of the Objector, let it be obſerved (with care) that the Word Teach, is twice mentioned in the Words of the Commiſſion; <hi>Go and Teach all Nations, Baptizing them;</hi> &amp;c. And in Ver. 20, <hi>Teaching them to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The firſt Teach is (in the Original) <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theteuſate;</hi> and the other is <hi>Didaskontes;</hi> which I chooſe to ſet down in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> (rather than in the <hi>Greek</hi>) Character, to the end the Unlearned may Read them; and (in Reading) obſerve the great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which is between the two Words, and that both in the Letters and Sound of the Words; if this be taken notice of, it
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:102079:35"/> will afford to the Unlearned (who would not be impos'd upon) ground to ſuſpect, not only the Skill (in Tongues,) but alſo the Honeſty and Faithfulneſs of thoſe Guides, whom they Judge come nearer to Infalibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in what they Teach, than do the other eminent Servants of Chriſt, who differ from them; and at whoſe Labours the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt Preachers of that Party, are glad to Light their Candles.</p>
            <p>As theſe two Words differ in Letters and Sound, as the Unlearned themſelves will find, (if they be but Faithful to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,) ſo they differ alſo in their Senſe and Signification, as the Orthodox and Learned well know. I begin with the firſt, <hi>(viz.) Matheteuſate,</hi> which ſignifies (properly) to Diſciple, or to make Diſciples in all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, where the Goſpel ſhall be (gladly) received.</p>
            <p>How is this to be done? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Even as God Taught <hi>Abraham,</hi> when he Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him in the great Myſtery of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: The which, when <hi>Abraham</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac'd for himſelf and his Infant-Seed, he received (gladly) the Viſible Token or Seal of that Covenant of Grace, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, and marks out his Infant-Seed, by putting the ſame Seal of the Covenant on them, and that in compliance with God's Command.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:102079:36"/>
            <p>It is but Rational to ſuppoſe and grant, that the firſt Subjects of an Ordinance ſhould be Perſons Adult, and Grown up to the uſe of Reaſon, that they may be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Acting for not only themſelves, but for their Off ſpring and Poſterity alſo, who are not (while Infants) capable of Acting for themſelves.</p>
            <p>This was God's Way and Method with <hi>Abraham</hi> (his Friend) he Propounds his Covenant of Grace to him and (in him) to his Seed, as their Stipulating and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting Head and Repreſentative. In In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing <hi>Abraham,</hi> God (in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Perſon) Inſtructs his Infants, ſo as by that Inſtruction, his Infant-Seed became Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and were (accordingly) Sign'd with the Seal of their Stipulating Father's Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
            <p>This (undoubtedly) was the Method which the Apoſtles went in, when they were ſent forth to make Diſciples (to Chriſt) in every Nation. They Inſtructed Adult and Grown Perſons in the Myſtery of God's Grace (by Chriſt;) and when ſuch laid hold on Chriſt (in the Covenant) by an External Profeſſion of Faith, (in him) they were Baptized with their Infants, (if any they had.) Hence we Read of the Jay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor in <hi>Acts</hi> 16.33. who (on his Believing) was Baptized, he and all that were of him,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:102079:36"/> 
               <hi>(viz.)</hi> His own Perſonal Off-ſpring, ſo the <hi>Greek</hi> Word ſignifies. Hence alſo we Read of whole Families, who were Baptized (by the Apoſtles) on the Faith of ſuch as were the Heads of ſuch Families. It was no more neceſſary, that Infants ſhould be made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of, (as being in ſuch Families when Baptized) than it was, that they ſhould be nam'd in the Grand Commiſſion; the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which gave out the Grand Commiſſion, was in, and with the Apoſtles, when they Baptized; and it is (to me) convincing, that Infants are intended in both, ſeeing they are excepted againſt, in neither, which the Adverſary muſt (needs) be convinc'd of, unleſs he be able to prove, that Infants are neither a part of Nations or of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.</p>
            <p>The other Word Teach in the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is, <hi>Didaskontes,</hi> which (properly) ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a Teaching or Inſtructing (Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally) thoſe, who are (already) made Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples by the former way of Teaching. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it (without Lying) be ſaid to be Nonſenſe and folly, to term Infants (who are by the firſt Teaching made Diſciples) Schollars or Diſciples, ſeeing, that Infants (in Age) are (by the Spirit of Truth) ſo ſtyl'd, witneſs <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10. where ſuch are called Diſciples, who were made ſo by the Initiating Ordinance of Circumciſion,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:102079:37"/> who afterwards (when grown up) were taught (Doctrinally) what they were to know and practice; neither is this (any whit) repugnant to the Method God took with <hi>Abraham,</hi> but rather agreeing with it; as appears by <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. and even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Men nothing more common and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, than to call our little Children Schollars or Diſciples, and that from the very firſt day of their being entred into a School: And as in Mens Schools there are ſundry Ranks or Claſſes of Schollars, ſome lower and ſome higher; ſo in the School of Chriſt (the great Prophet of his Church) there are ſeveral Ranks or Degrees of Church Members. It is well known how ignorant (in the Myſteries of the Goſpel) the very Apoſtles themſelves were, when they firſt entred into Chriſts School; yet Chriſt calls them his Diſciples for all that. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> could not write or ſpeak unto the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> but as unto Babes, as unto Carnal Men; yet they were Church Members for all that. Theſe things duly conſidered, forces me to conclude thoſe Men profoundly ignorant in the Myſtery of Gods Holy Covenant; who (becauſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are uncapable of being taught and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed (Doctrinally) as adult and grown Men are) peremptorily deny that Infants are capable of being made Diſciples (to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:102079:37"/> Chriſt) by the Miniſtry of Men. This Principle came (no doubt) from the ſame Spirit which teaches that Infants, (while Infants) are uncapable of Regeneration; which are both (manifeſtly) falſe, becauſe contrary to Gods revealed Will.</p>
            <p>Object. 3. <hi>Baptiſm is a Seal of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Faith, to which none have a right, but he or ſhe who is a real true Believer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer in three particulars. Firſt, If Baptiſm be a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith, then muſt it needs ſucceed and come in the room of Circumciſion: And ſo the truth is (here) granted, which elſe where is denied, that Circumciſion is a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith; is moſt plain from <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. Now if Baptiſm be a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith, (as the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jector grants, and as I believe and affirm it is) then Baptiſm did (undeniably) come in the room of Circumciſion, that the ſame might be to Believing Gentiles (under the Goſpel) what Circumciſion was (of Old) to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, (viz.)</hi> a Seal of the Covenant of Grace.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If none but actual Believers have a Right to that Righteouſneſs of w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ich Baptiſm is a Seal, then muſt it follow (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably) that all Infants (who Dye in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy) are Eternally loſt: And how (cruel this Doctrine is, and how inconſiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt with
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:102079:38"/> the Doctrine which teacheth that all Infants (Dying Infants) are ſaved, all Men may ſee.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If none but real true Believers have a Right to Baptiſm, I would gladly ſee how thoſe (I Diſpute againſt) can juſtify their own practices, in admitting ſo many poor ignorant Folk to that Ordinance (in their way) who (with ſome who admit them) are as ignorant of the Myſtery of Regeneration and of Baptiſm, (the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Seal thereof) as was <hi>Nicodemus.</hi> Can they (without a Divine Revelation) know that thoſe whom they admit to Baptiſm are (infallibly) real true Believers?</p>
            <p>Object. 4. <hi>To apply Baptiſm, (the Seal of the Covenant) to an unintelligent Subject, who neither knows what is done to him, nor yields conſent thereto: It is all one as to preſent a Picture to a Blind Man, which to do is moſt abſurd and ridiculous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this I ſhall reply in four par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. And firſt, I ſay (with a Learned Man) this is (at beſt) but a blind Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon; and (which is far worſe) a high and fancy Reflection on the infinite Wiſdom and uncontroulable Soveraignty of the moſt high God; for moſt certain it is, that nothing can be offered as an Argument to keep Infants from Baptiſm, (meerly) on the account of their being unintelligent Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:102079:38"/> and uncapable of yielding their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to what is done to them in Baptiſm) But what will be of as great force to keep them back from Circumciſion? And ſo the Objector may ſee (plainly) how (herein) he arraigns the Wiſdom and Soveraignty of God at the Bar of a ſhallow and corrupt Creatures Reaſon, which demonſtrates him to be more Brutiſh; (I am ſure more proud end wicked) than thoſe Non-intelligent Subjects which the Objection is levelled againſt.</p>
            <p>This will appear by conſidering Gods dealing with <hi>Abraham,</hi> in that he command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to Mark (or Seal) his Son <hi>Iſaac</hi> with the Seal of Circumciſion at Eight Days old. Had <hi>Iſaac</hi> the uſe of reaſon at that Age? Had he actual Faith or Speech to expreſs his conſent to what was (then) done to him? No ſure; what then muſt God be charged with weakneſs or unreaſonableneſs for applying the Seal of his Covenant to an unintelligent Subject? By theſe kind of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors, Gods Act (herein) ſtands charged with weakneſs and folly, but I conclude with <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 3.4. <hi>Yea, let God be true, but every Man a Lyar.</hi> God commands nothing in vain, and the reaſon is, becauſe his Ordinance hath no kind of dependence on the Creature, to give it power, or to make it effectual to accompliſh what he hath
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:102079:39"/> appointed it to, but on his own free Spirit, which works moſt powerfully, yea, irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtably where he himſelf hath purpoſed to confer the Spiritual Good, ſignified by the outward Ordinance.</p>
            <p>Object. 5. <hi>The Promiſe of Gods Covenant is made to the Elect, and none but they have a Right to the Seal: No Man can affirm that an Infant brought to Baptiſm is Elect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I Anſwer to this in two things. Firſt, I grant that none ſhall ever reap any ſaving Benefit by the Covenant, but the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect; (and that in the right of Election) yet doth it not hence follow, that none but they have a right to the Seal of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in the Church Viſible, ſeeing that by the very Conſtitution of Gods Covenant (with <hi>Abraham</hi> the Eccleſiaſtical Father, and pub ick Viſible Head of all the Seed of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Church-Members) God commands that the Seal of his Covenant ſhall be equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apply'd to all the Male-Seed of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever; and that without any regard to the Election, which is a Secret known (only) to God; about which he would not have us to trouble our Spirits, any farther than to give all (becoming) diligence to make our own (Pe ſonal) Election ſure to our ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lves. As touchi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g the Infants of Church Memb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, (about whom all the Diſpute is) We are not (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nxiouſly) to be concerned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:102079:39"/> them, whether they be in the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God, yea or no. It is ground ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for us to Bleſs and thank God for his dealing ſo Graciouſly with our Infants, in that they (with us) are taken into the ſame Covenant, and Sealed with the Seal there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; for by Gods dealing thus with Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Infant-Seed, Believers have a good foundation laid, whereon to bottom their Hope and Comfort, (with reference to thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Dying or Deceaſed Infants) and alſo of wreſtling with God in Prayer for their Converſion and Eternal Welfare; the which the Enemies to Infant-Baptiſm, do (by denying that Infants belong to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt, or have any right to the Promiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s thereof, till they themſelves B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lieve) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive, and (inſenſibly) ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oil themſelves of. This is moſt evidently true, as will appear if it be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riouſly conſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ered, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all right Prayer is a Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g the Promiſes of Gods Covenant, in the Name and Merit of Chriſt his own So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, in and through whom, the ſaid Promiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s are intail'd on all the Children of Promiſe: Now if my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant be Sick or Ailing? If he be going on in Sin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> how can I (by the Anabaptiſt Principle put up a Prayer to God for him, ſeeing there is no promiſe of Gods Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant belongs to him? Or how can I comfort my ſorrowful Spirit (with reference to my
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:102079:40"/> Deceaſed Children) if I muſt look on my dear Babes as Strangers and Enemies to God, (the which they are by Nature; and muſt remain ſo for ever) in caſe they be not Partakers of the Grace of Gods Covenant?</p>
            <p>Secondly, If none but the Elect have right to Baptiſm, this Objection will fall like a Mill-ſtone on them who Baptize whole droves of Men and Women; of whoſe Election (to Eternal Life) neither Baptizer nor Baptized, know any more than they know how many Stars in the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo that by thus arguing againſt poor Tongue-ty'd Infants, they may ſee how they deny Salvation to their own (as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll as others) Infants, and render themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of diſcharging a good Conſcience to their poor Children, in putting up (dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) Petitions to God for them.</p>
            <p>Object. 6. <hi>We have an open Profeſſion from thoſe we Baptize, and that warrants our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing ſuch as offer themſelves to join to the Churches. You have not the like from Infants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I Anſwer hereto in three parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars. Firſt, it were well for both Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers and Baptized, if both the one and the other were better acquainted with the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of right Converſion than they are, and that they were better grounded in the ſound (and experimental) knowledge of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace; the which if they were,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:102079:40"/> I dare (boldly) ſay, they would not be ſo precipitant and raſh in condemning and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing thoſe poor Infants, who are ſet forth (by the Wiſdom of God) as Patterns and Examples, by which grown Perſons are to be moulded and ſitted for Heaven: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would they be ſo forward to offer themſelves to Baptiſm on ſuch ſlight and evanid Motions, as falls ſhort (in too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) of common Convictions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, poor Infants never (yet) broke or tranſgreſſed the Moral Law, (Perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) and that is one great reaſon why an actual confeſſion of Faith and Repentance is not required of them, to qualifie them for Baptiſm: As the Sin of Infants lyes in the imputation of <hi>Adams</hi> Diſobedience, and the Pollution of Nature, derived by fleſhly Generation; ſo their help and remedy lyes in the imputation of Chriſts Spotleſs Righteouſneſs to their Perſons; and his Spirits renewing their inward Faculties in Regenerating them. And this twofold work of the Spirit in Juſtifying and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the Elect Infant, is (plainly) ſignifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and Sealed in that Ordinance of Baptiſm, to the Infant, as well as to a grown <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eliever.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, albeit Infants be not able to ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k for themſelves, and to claim that right to the Seal of Gods Covenant which the Covenant it ſelf hath entail'd on them,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:102079:41"/> (as they are the Church Seed of Believing Parents) yet there is one who ſpeaks for them, whoſe Judgment and Teſtimony of them is more ſure and infallible than all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Teſtimonies of Men and Angels; the Lord Jeſus (I mean) who (with his Father, and God the Holy Ghoſt) contrived and made the Covenant of Grace, wherein they are comprehended. I will lay down in ſix Particulars what is the Judgment of Chriſt concerning Infants, (as they are concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Covenant) Firſt, he propounds them as Patterns, by which grown Perſons muſt be moulded and fitted for Heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.3. Secondly, declares their right to the Kingdom of God, <hi>Mar</hi> 10.14. <hi>For of ſuch is the Kingdom of God.</hi> Thirdly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes (moſt ſeverely) his Diſciples for hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Infants being brought to him, <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.14. <hi>But when Jeſus ſaw it, he was much diſpleaſed,</hi> &amp;c. In the Greek it is <hi>Eganak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſe,</hi> which ſignifies to have the Bowels (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly) moved, or affected with Grief, to be filled with Indignation; (as <hi>Beza</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it, <hi>Indignatus eſt,</hi> to be Stomackt at a Perſon, or a thing which is greatly or highly diſpleaſing: A Word which judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Sydenham</hi> obſerves, was never uſed by Chriſt in any caſe, or on any occaſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this of poor Infants, to inſtruct and teach Men: (No doubt) how greatly he
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:102079:41"/> was concerned for helpleſs Infants, and how diſpleaſed he was at the hardneſs of his Diſciples Hearts againſt them: Oh! that the conſideration of this might melt the hard Hearts of ſuch, into a Chriſt like tenderneſs towards poor Infants. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, commands Infants to be brought to him, <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.14. <hi>Suffer little Children to come unto me,</hi> &amp;c. Fifthly, pronounces them Holy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. Sixthly, Bleſſeth them, <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.16. <hi>And he took them up in his Arms, laid his Hands upon them and Bleſſed them.</hi> Theſe ſix Particulars laid together, and weighed in the Ballance of Gods Sanctuary, I leave it to any Man of Senſe (in Spiritual matters) to judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is ſafer to credit this infallible Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Son of God, concerning In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, than to rely on the bare Teſtimony of a meer Man, concerning himſelf; who may (in all he pretends to) be but a Paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sepulchre.</p>
            <p>Object. 7. <hi>If Infants muſt needs have a right to Baptiſm, becauſe it is a Seal of the Covenant, then (of neceſſity) they muſt have a right to the Lords Supper alſo; for that is a Seal of the Covenant of Grace as well as Baptiſm. The Wine in the Supper might as well be poured down the Infants mouth with a Spoon, as to ſprinkle Water on his face.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Objection better becomes
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:102079:42"/> a Superannuated Man, who borders on perfect Dotage, than one who pretends to be a Teacher of ignorant and miſguided Souls; and not only ſo, but who takes on him to Uſurp the Seat of Judgment, in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Sentence on all the Holy, Learned and Orthodox Divines, and Proteſtant Martyrs and Churches, who are gone to Glory in the unſhaken Belief that the Infants of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Parents have an unqueſtionable right to Baptiſm, and that they are as capable of the Seal of Baptiſm as they are of the Grace of Gods Covenant, ſignified thereby.</p>
            <p>But that the Lords Supper belongs to none but to Adult and actual Believers, who are capable of thoſe qualifications required in a worthy Communicant; ſuch as Self-examination, (with reference to his State Godward) his faith in Chriſt, his progreſs in a Holy Life, his diſcerning the Lords Body, his keeping up a lively Communion with Father, Son and Spirit in that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and judging ones ſelf in caſe of ſhort coming in Holy Duties.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the qualifications required to be in one who comes to the Lords Supper; of which, any (not in a Dream) may judge an Infant cannot be capable, (while an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant.) I humbly hope no judicious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an will cenſure me (as raſh and uncharitable) if I judge thoſe Preachers fitter for a Shop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:102079:42"/> than a Pulpit, who are not able or willing to diſcern or diſtinguiſh between Milk and ſtrong Meat; and who will deny to Infants the Milk of Holy Baptiſm, (whereof they are capable, and whereto (by Gods Covenant) they have right, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are uncapable of receiving and digeſting the ſtrong Meat of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Object. 8. <hi>If Infant-Baptiſm were God's Ordinance, and were accompanied with his Bleſſing, to the Infant, how comes it to paſs, that ſo many Baptized, (in Infancy) prove ſo Carnal and looſe in their Lives and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hereto I reply in three Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, wherewith I ſhall ſhut up the preſent Diſpute.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is with many Believers Infants now (under the Goſpel) as it was with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and his Infants of old. Some are their Children by fleſhly Generation only, who (<hi>Iſhmael</hi>-like) prove Mockers and Scoffers at Holineſs, and Haters of God and good Men: Theſe, (notwithſtanding the Relation they ſtand in to the Church, by Virtue of their Baptiſmal Vow and the External Profeſſion they make in the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church for a time) being left to the darkneſs and folly lodged in their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Nature, they give themſelves over
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:102079:43"/> to all kind of Looſeneſs. Baptiſm (now) is no more to be faulted on this account, than Circumciſion was formerly.</p>
            <p>When the Children of believing <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> do (actually) violate God's Covenant, and depart from him; then will God do with them, as he did with <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Seed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As ſome of the Children of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Parents, who were Baptiz'd in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant State, prove looſe and vain, ſo (Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God) a great many prove Holy and Upright Walkers with God, manifeſting in their Lives and Converſations, the live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Coppy of that Spiritual Circumciſion wrought (by the Spirit) in their Hearts when Converted, which was Signified and Sealed by that Baptiſm, which they were made Partakers of when Infants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly and laſtly,</hi> If from the vain and ſinful Practiſe of ſome (Baptiz'd in Infancy) Infant-Baptiſm, muſt be diſallow'd, (as no Inſtitution of God,) how ſtrong an Argument will this prove, to overthrow the Baptizing grown Profeſſors? For (if I miſtake not) the Oppoſers of Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm muſt own, (will they nill they) that many of thoſe Baptiz'd (in their way) have (notwithſtanding their ſhining Profeſſion, and their high Pretenſions to the Work of the Spirit within) fallen moſt foully, and never recover'd again.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:102079:43"/>
            <p>And thus I have (according to the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom given from above) endeavoured to clear up, (from God's Word) that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. is (moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly) the Covenant of Grace. I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo prov'd (from the ſame Word,) that Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was the Seal of that Covenant: And that Baptiſm (under the Goſpel) is now ſucceeded (or come in the room) thereof. I have endeavoured to prove, that the Infants of believing <hi>Gentiles</hi> have as real a Right to Baptiſm as <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed had to Circumciſion, under that dark Diſpenſation. And whether the Anſwers I have given to the moſt material Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I find brought againſt Infant-Baptiſm, be pertinent and convincing, I leave to the Judicious and Unprejudic'd to Judge.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. V.</head>
            <p>AMong all the Raſh and Preſumptuous Aſſertors of Dipping the whole Body under Water, being the only right Mode or Manner of Baptizing, none hath made a greater noiſe (or a fairer ſhew) of being (herein) Infalible, than one <hi>William Ruſſel,</hi> who ſtyles himſelf <hi>Medicinae Doctor, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cademiae Cantabrigienſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Author, with a more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:102079:44"/> Confidence, hath boldly aſſerted; that Dipping, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is the only right Mode of Baptizing, commanded by Chriſt in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> and practiſed by <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, and all the Apoſtles and Primitive Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>This crude (or raw) Aſſertion of his, he labours to ſupport and make good by a fourfold <hi>Medium: Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Etymologie</hi> of the <hi>Greek</hi> word the Holy Ghoſt uſeth to expreſs Dipping by.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Thoſe Metaphors uſed in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, to repreſent it to our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Practiſe of the firſt Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The words of the Grand Commiſſion given by our Saviour in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.</p>
            <p>To demonſtrate the falſeneſs of his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, and to diſcover to Weak and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicious People the great Miſtakes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he bottoms his Aſſertion, is the deſign of my preſent Undertaking. But before I attack this <hi>Goliah,</hi> in examining what he can get from the four Particulars (above mentioned,) which may cauſe Simple and empty Brains to think and conceit this Accademical Doctor Invincible and Unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable in what he hath (ſo Peremptori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) aſſerted for the Truth of God. I will
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:102079:44"/> lay down two things, (by way of Premiſe) whereof I deſire the Reader (who is unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be deceiv'd) to take notice.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, That not ſo much the bare Letter of Scripture, as the ſenſe and meaning of the Spirit, (therein) is the Word of God; by which Truth and Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror are to be Try'd and Judg'd. I have often ſaid, (and I am very bold in affirming, that) that Senſe or Interpretation, which any Man or Men give of any Text of God's Word, which thwarts and contradicts the Analogie of Faith, that Senſe or Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is from the Spirit of Satan; not from God, be the ſame never ſo plauſible and pleaſing to the Sons of Men; and be the Authors never ſo highly eſteem'd of, for both their Piety and Learning. There is a ſweet and an harmonious Concord and Agreement between all the parts of God's Revealed Religion, though but few (Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively) can ſee it to be ſo. The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Inſtitutions of God in all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of his Inſtituted Worſhip, are plain, eaſy and obvious to the Eye, which the Spirit of Chriſt hath Anointed: But to ſuch Men and Women, who are Deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the Spirit of Chriſt, nothing in Religion appears to them, but Nonſenſe and ſeeming Contradictions, which is the Reaſon why ſo many thouſands in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:102079:45"/> &amp;c. Stagger and Reel (with a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <hi>Vertigo</hi>) in the Principles of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, wherein both they and their Anceſtors were Initiated (by Water-Baptiſm;) and in maintaining of which, they ſeemed (for many years) very Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing I ſhall Premiſe, is this, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That Heterodox and Corrupt Underminers of the Goſpel are then to be moſt of all lookt after and watcht againſt, when they lay about them, to advance the Fame and Credit of the Devil's Miniſters, by Ecclipſing and Darkening the Credit and deſerved Fame of Chriſt's Worthys, whom Chriſt hath Honoured with, being the chief Combatants in the Lord's Battels againſt the Powers of Darkneſs in this World.</p>
            <p>My deſign in this, is to diſcover to the unwary Reader, this Doctor's Deſign of Blackening that Renowned and Incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Servant of Chriſt, Mr. <hi>John Calvin,</hi> than whom, I verily believe, the World hath not (ſince the Apoſtles left the Earth) ſeen a Greater Divine. A Man, who (for his high and excellent Endowments in all manner of Learning, eſpecially his Eagle-eyedneſs, in penetrating into the Senſe of Scriptures) was more like a Prophet, or an Apoſtle, than an ordinary Preacher.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:102079:45"/>
            <p>This Doctor, that he might put a Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre on <hi>Michael Servetus</hi> his Name, draws the Pencil of horrid and black Reproach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croſs the Name and Reputation of Holy, and (as I ſaid) Incomparable <hi>Calvin.</hi> The Devil (in his Miniſters) being deeply ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible how the famous and elaborate Works of that one Man ſtand in the way, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and hinder the Devil growing Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant, in advancing his Kingdom of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs among the Sons of Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calvin</hi> is (by the Dr.) repreſented as an ambitious, Self ſeeking Man; and (which is far worſe) a bloody Perſecuter, while his <hi>Servetus</hi> is deckt and adorned wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the Robes of a Glorious Martyrdom. The Drs. Words will ſhew whether I be miſtaken in what I ſay of him, ſee Page 4 of the Drs. Epiſtle, where he ſaith, (with a Spirit of virulency) and at laſt I concluded it muſt certainly proceed from the very Spirit and Principle of the firſt founder of your Sect, (meaning the <hi>Presbyterians</hi>) Maſter <hi>John Calvin,</hi> who burnt the Books of <hi>Servetus,</hi> a Learned Baptiſt, and afterwards perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Magiſtrates of <hi>Geneva</hi> to Burn him alive; which Sentence was executed upon him, (as <hi>Caſtellio</hi> teſtifies, (who was a contemporary with him) In theſe words <hi>Michael Servetus</hi> was burnt alive for his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, at <hi>Geneva,</hi> 1553, upon the 27th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay of <hi>October.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:102079:46"/>
            <p>Beſides this, The Dr. tells his Reader, (with an ungodly deſign, to leſſen and blacken the Famous <hi>Calvin;</hi> and to Extol his <hi>Servetus,</hi>) that one well obſerves, that Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> did acknowledge of <hi>Servetus,</hi> that he was a Learned Charitable Man; notwithſtanding which, he wrote a Book to Juſtifie <hi>Servetus</hi> being put to Death.</p>
            <p>When I See and Rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe things, from a better, and more Impartial Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony than <hi>Caſtellio</hi> was, I ſhall then ſay ſomewhat to it. But (indeed) I muſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly aſſure the Dr. that I ſhall neither believe him, nor his <hi>Caſtellio,</hi> in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports they ſpread abroad of <hi>Calvin,</hi> and others (of Chriſt's Worthys) who Detect and Decry their Heretical Doctrines.</p>
            <p>Not him, becauſe ſad Experience Teaches, that thoſe of his Judgement are pretty well Skilled, in Miſrepreſenting and Belying the moſt Holy, Orothodox, and moſt Learned of Divines; on purpoſe to gain Ground among the leſs Intelligent, whom they know to be ſtrangers to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors; and who will be eaſily drawn to Credit thoſe Reports, which they are not able to contradict: Eſpecially when Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to them, by the Mouth and Pen, of ſuch, as they take to be good Men.</p>
            <p>Not his <hi>Caſtellio,</hi> becauſe I look on him every way as unfit to be a Witneſs
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:102079:46"/> againſt ſo Orthodox and great a Propugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of Goſpel Verities, as <hi>Calvin</hi> is known to be; And that, on the Account of the Teſtimonies given of <hi>Caſtellio;</hi> by good and Learned Men, who better knew what <hi>Caſtellio</hi> was than Dr. <hi>Ruſſel</hi> doth.</p>
            <p>The Great and Learned <hi>Scaliger</hi> charges <hi>Caſtellio,</hi> with holding many corrupt Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the Anabaptiſts.</p>
            <p>And the Learned <hi>Hoffman</hi> Accuſed him for being one of the firſt Sowers of the Seed of <hi>Arminianiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tar. Faber,</hi> another Great and Learned Author, Charged him with ſaying that the Song of <hi>Solomon</hi> was a Wicked Book. And he held that <hi>Paul</hi> Taught a more Myſterious Divinity to ſome perfect Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, than he left in Wri ing, this is to be ſeen in his Book, on the Firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the Impartial Reader, ſeriouſly weighs the Account given of <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Caſtellio,</hi> by the Orthodox and Learned, he will ſoon conclude (with me,) That had the Parts and Learning of <hi>Servetus</hi> and <hi>Caſtellio</hi> both Concenter'd in one Head, <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Orthodoxy in the Faith, and his Excellency in all manner of Learning, had never been in danger of Suffering an Eclipſe: Nor yet his Books of receiving a Solid Anſwer (much leſs a Confutation) by
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:102079:47"/> ſuch Men as <hi>Servetus</hi> and <hi>Caſtellio,</hi> whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Dr. <hi>Ruſſel</hi> and his Bigotted Proſelites think or believe to the Contrary.</p>
            <p>That Eagle Eyed <hi>Calvin,</hi> ſoared too High (in Penetrating into the <hi>Arcana Imperii</hi> of Heaven) for ſuch Glow-worms to reach his Senſe, or to underſtand the Spirit by which he Speaks and Writes. <hi>Wiſdom is Juſtified of none but her own Legitimate Off-ſpring.</hi> Mat. 11.19.</p>
            <p>And here I deſire the wary Reader, to take notice of the fraudulent deſign of Dr. <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> which is, to I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>poſe on his Reader, a believing that <hi>Servetus</hi> (who dy'd at <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva</hi> for his Opinion) did Dye for b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing an Anabaptiſt: which inded is a notorious Piece of Falſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood, as the Learned and Godly (who look into Antiquity) well know, who give that Account of <hi>Servetus,</hi> that he was Executed at <hi>Geneva</hi> for his Blaſphemy ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inſt the Holy Trinity, he Denying the God-Head of Chriſt, and the Perſonality of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>This the Dr. well knew would have ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his deſign, had he (honeſtly) told his Reader, what an Heterodox and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Wretch, his <hi>Servetus,</hi> that Learned Baptiſt (who Dy'd at <hi>Geneva</hi> for his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) was.</p>
            <p>And truly, (to be plain,) had <hi>Servetus</hi> Dy'd for being an Anabaptiſt (which I ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:102079:47"/> deny he did,) yet, I am far from thinking the better of Anabaptiſm therefore: Or, Judging <hi>Servetus,</hi> (or any others who on that Account looſe their Lives) to be true Martyrs of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
            <p>That ſaying of <hi>Cyprian</hi> will ever be true, that <hi>Cauſa, non Mors, facit Martirem,</hi> The Cauſe, not Death, makes a Martyr. As the Bleſſed Jeſus hath his Witneſſes, who Seal the Word of his Patience, with their deareſt Blood.</p>
            <p>So the Devil hath his Witneſſes, (yea, many more than Chriſt hath,) who Seal their Infernal Hereſies, and Damnable Doctrines, with their Hearts Blood; yet I am far from Believing that ſuch Martyrs, will ever be owned by Chriſt, at their going off the Stage: Or, that ſuch Sufferings will make better the horrid Lyes and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies Men Suffer for, be their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, ſeeming Zeal, and Courage what it will.</p>
            <p>Having Premiſed theſe things, I now proceed, to Examine the Four Particulars, whereon his Fabrick of Anabaptiſm ſeems to be Founded.</p>
            <p>The Dr. and (with him all Anabaptiſts) Hold, (and with great Confidence) Aſſert: that Dipping and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lungeing the whole Body under Water, is the Only Right
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:102079:48"/> manner of Baptiſm, which all Believers are to practiſe under the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>This he labours, (though in vain) to make good by the Etymologie of the word, which the Spirit uſes to expreſs Baptiſm by.</p>
            <p>The word (in the Greek) is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which (ſaith the Dr.) is derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to Dip or Plunge a thing under water. This ſignification of the Primitive word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he confirms by Human Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; he begins with Learned Mr. <hi>Leigh,</hi> to whoſe <hi>Critica Sacra</hi> he refers his Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, in Quoting whom, he deals with his Reader as he did in Quoting <hi>Servetus;</hi> he ſaith that <hi>Servetus</hi> Dy'd at <hi>Geneva</hi> for his Opinion, but hides from his Reader the horrid Blaſphemies for which he Dyed: So here the Dr. (deſigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) Curtails the Obſervations of Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi> on the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, telling his Reader ſo much out of Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi> as he thinks makes for his Cauſe, but leaving out what of Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi> he knows makes full againſt him; which (I muſt needs ſay) is the trick of a Deceiver: And by theſe kind of ſhifts he and the moſt Crafty of his Party, do endeavour to underprop their ſinking Cauſe, bearing poor ſimple folk in hand, that the Eminently Learned and Godly Men (whom they Quote) were of the Anabaptiſts Perſwaſion.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:102079:48"/>
            <p>Now to let his unfairneſs appear herein, I here ſet down what of <hi>Leigh</hi> he quotes, and what of him he omits.</p>
            <p>The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Leigh,</hi> is derived from the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Tingo,</hi> to Dip or Plunge into the Water; and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth (primarily) ſuch a kind of waſhing as is uſed in Bucks, where Linnen is plunged and dipt. Thus far the Dr. Quotes <hi>Leigh,</hi> and who would not think by reading ſo much of <hi>Leigh,</hi> and looking no further, (as the Dr. no doubt would have his Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) but that <hi>Leigh</hi> in his <hi>Critica Sacra</hi> was of the Drs. judgment herein.</p>
            <p>Now follows the Learned <hi>Leighs</hi> Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations on the ſignification of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. yet (ſaith he) it is taken more largely (meaning <hi>Baptizo</hi>) for any kind of waſhing, rinſing or cleanſing, even where there is no Dipping at all; for which he Quotes <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. <hi>I indeed Baptize you with Water,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.22. <hi>Are ye able to be Baptized with,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mar.</hi> 7.4. <hi>And when they come from the Market, except they waſh they eat not.</hi> Luke 3.16. Acts 1.5. Acts 11.16. and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2. In all which Scriptures Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi> doth acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (the Derivative) is of a larger ſignification then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> its Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and intends ſuch a waſhing as is done
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:102079:49"/> without Dipping; and why ſhould this be concealed from the Reader?</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Zeppeorus, Alſtedius, Plutarch</hi> and <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> (on whom the Dr. lays no ſmall ſtreſs) I hope he will allow us the ſame liberty he takes to himſelf, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to Quote ſuch Teſtimonies as make for us.</p>
            <p>The Learned Dr. featly (Quoted by Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi>) tells us that Chriſt no where requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth Dipping, but only Baptizing; which word (ſaith he) <hi>Heſychius, Stephanus, Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pula</hi> and <hi>Budeus,</hi> the great Maſters of the Greek Tongue) make good by very many Inſtances and Allegations out of Claſſick Writers, that the word importeth no more then Ablution or Waſhing, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſay they) in their Lexicons and Commentaries) <hi>Lavo</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lavatio, Ablutio,</hi> which may be done without Dipping.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As touching the Greek Lexicon, Publiſht, and recommended by.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Joſeph Caryl,</item>
               <item>George Cokayne,</item>
               <item>Ralph Venning,</item>
               <item>William Dell,</item>
               <item>Matthew Barker,</item>
               <item>William Adderly,</item>
               <item>Matthew Mead,</item>
               <item>Henry Jeſſey.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All that I ſhall (or need to) ſay, is this, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that albeit I own my ſelf bound to Reverence and Honour the hoary Head, when found in the way of Truth and Righteouſneſs, yet it muſt ſtill be with the reſervation of the honour and reſpect which
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:102079:49"/> I owe to God, (that Ancient of Days) their Father and mine, who alone and not the Learning and Wiſdom of Men, (though the Greateſt and Holieſt) is the Father of their Faith and mine. I am not inſenſible that ſome Learned and good Men have granted, that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently ſignifie, any kind of Waſhing by pouring out or ſprinkling Water upon, or, by Dipping or Plunging into the Water; and this they have grounded on the native Signification of the Primitive word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But with becoming modeſty and due vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to their Reverend Names, I muſt crave leave in telling the World, that for a World I cannot be of their Opinion (here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) until I receive greater and clearer light from the Spirit and Word of God, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this matter; and that for the reaſons here following. Firſt, the apparent differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence I find between the two Words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in Letters and Syllables, let the words be obſerved, in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive) I can find but 2 Syllables, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Bap-to,</hi> but in the Derivative <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> I find three, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Baptizo,</hi> and as in the Active, (ſo alſo in the Paſſive) Voice, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Bap-to-mai</hi> hath three Syllables, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is the Paſſive of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hath four Syllables, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Bap-ti-zo-mai.</hi> Now that the 2 words ſhould both
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:102079:50"/> in Active and Paſſive Voice ſo apparently differ in Letters, Syllables, and ſound of the words; and yet, that both the words ſhould ſignifie and import the very ſame thing, is to me ſuch a Riddle, that indeed I cannot ſee how the ſame can be unfolded, unleſs by the elucidating Art, and skill of Dr. <hi>Ruſſel.</hi> The Learned know (very well) that in the Hebrew and Greek Tongues, the change of a Letter or a Syllable doth great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alter the Senſe and Import of Words; and why it ſhould not be ſo here, I cannot ſee any ſolid reaſon to the contrary, only it is the Will and Pleaſure of our Dr. (and his Adherents in this Cauſe) that it muſt and ſhall be ſo, right or wrong; as appears by his Arminian Confidence almoſt in every Page where he mentions the Word Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize; where he (peremptorily) beggs the Queſtion, taking for granted, that which will never be granted by any, (unleſs by Brainleſs Heads or wilful underminers of the Goſpel, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that the Derivative <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth always (in the Goſpel) ſignifie and import the very ſame thing with <hi>Bapto, (viz.)</hi> to Dip or Plunge the whole Body under Water.</p>
            <p>But that which will farther clear the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and put the Truth (I here contend for) out of the reach of all Scriptural Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, is the Practice of the Holy Ghoſt,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:102079:50"/> who is better Etymologiſt than our Dr. and then all the Arminian (and other Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical) Criticks, who (in pretence of giving the Native and Genuine ſenſe of Words in the Scripture) have forc't a wrong ſenſe from the Original, on purpoſe to lay a firm foundation, on which they may build their Heterodox, and Soul deluding Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines.</p>
            <p>I find that when the Holy Ghoſt would expreſs the Act of Dipping or Plunging in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, he doth it only by the Primitive <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, never by the Derivative <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that I can find: For Proof whereof, let thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (Quoted by the Dr. himſelf in Page 11.) be without prejudice lookt into, and ſeriouſly weighed. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13. <hi>He had his Veſture dipt in Blood.</hi> Mat. 26.23. <hi>He that dippeth his hand with me in the Diſh.</hi> Luke 16.24. <hi>That he may dip the tip of his finger in Water.</hi> And in John 13.26. it is (ſaith the Dr.) twice uſed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Dipped, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>and when he had Dipped:</hi> Here in theſe places the Holy Ghoſt expreſſeth the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Dip or Plunge into by the Primitive <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but never by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Baptizo</hi> the Derivative.</p>
            <p>Secondly, again (on the contrary) when the Holy Ghoſt expreſſeth Baptiſm by waſhing, he doth it by the Derivative <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but never by the Primitive <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:102079:51"/> For Proof hereof, let the places of Scripture already quoted (out of <hi>Leigh's Critica Sacra</hi>) be conſulted, in all which places the Spirit ſpeaks of Baptiſm, but not a word of Dipping; and that by the Deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Baptizo;</hi> never by the Primitive <hi>Bapto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing then it hath pleaſed the Holy Ghoſt to expreſs Dipping or Plunging into by the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but never by the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Baptizo;</hi> and that he hath expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Baptiſm by the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but never by the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I think none but Fools or mad Men will blame me for reſolving to believe the Holy Ghoſt (in this matter) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I believe Dr. <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> and all the human Teſtimonies he hath quoted to make good his Cauſe; though he were able to quote a Million of Authors as Witty and Learned as his ſo much admired <hi>Servetus</hi> and <hi>Caſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Premiſſes conſidered, I hope the Dr. will not be diſpleaſed for making this fair and generous offer to him, and all who eſpouſe his Unſcriptural Cauſe, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that if he (or they) can ſhew ſuch a ſolid and convincing reaſon (as doth not contradict the Analogie of Faith) why (or wherefore) the Holy Ghoſt ſhould not in any of thoſe Scriptures (where he expreſſeth Dipping) expreſs Dipping by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Derivative,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:102079:51"/> but only by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Primitive; and why he ſhould not expreſs Baptiſm in any of the places of Scripture above quoted, by the Primitive <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Bapto,</hi> but always by <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizo,</hi> in caſe both <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Primitive, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> its Derivative do ſignifie the very ſame thing, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to Dip or Plunge under the Water: And I do faithfully promiſe him to own my ſelf miſtaken, and him to be (herein) in the right.</p>
            <p>If he cannot, I then hope his miſguided Proſelytes as well as himſelf, will ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly own themſelves miſtaken, and perſiſt no longer in fighting againſt the truth of God.</p>
            <p>From the difference between the two words in Letters, Syllables and Sound; as alſo from the Practice of the Holy Ghoſt, in uſing both the words in the N. T</p>
            <p>I thus Argue, Major. If the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> do apparently differ in Letters, Syllables and Sound, and if the Holy Ghoſt do always expreſs the Act of Dipping and Plunging by <hi>Bapto,</hi> never by <hi>Baptizo;</hi> and Baptiſm by <hi>Baptizo,</hi> never by <hi>Bapto;</hi> then the word <hi>Bapto</hi> muſt ſignifie to Dip and Plunge, but never to Baptize; and the word <hi>Baptizo</hi> muſt ſignifie to Baptize, but never to Dip or Plunge under Water.</p>
            <p>Aſſump. <hi>But the words</hi> Bapto and Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zo <hi>do apparently differ in Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ters, Syllables
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:102079:52"/> and Sound; and the Holy Ghoſt doth always expreſs the Act of Dipping or Plunging by</hi> Bapto, <hi>never by</hi> Baptizo; <hi>and Baptiſm by</hi> Baptizo, <hi>never by</hi> Bapto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concluſion, Ergo</hi> the word <hi>Bapto</hi> muſt ſignifie to Dip or Plunge, but never to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize; and the word <hi>Baptizo</hi> muſt ſignifie to Baptize, but never to Dip or Plunge un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Water.</p>
            <p>Beſides this Argument, others ſhall be laid down to confirm this when I come to ſpeak to his third, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Practice of the firſt Baptizers.</p>
            <p>In the 2d place, our Dr. will have Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing to be only by Dipping or Plunging the whole Body under Water: The Proof he gives (to make good his Aſſertion here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) are thoſe Metaphors uſed in Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: To repreſent it to our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he Inſtances in two, in Page 8, <hi>(viz)</hi> Burial and Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>He tells his Reader there, that our Lord Jeſus hath not burdened us under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel with a multitude of Ceremonies, as it was in the Oeconomy of the Jews under the Legal Diſpenſation, but only with ſome few; and thoſe very Significant, this being a more Spiritual Diſpenſation. Before I meddle in ſpeaking to his Metaphors, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill take liberty to tell the World, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eit Chriſt doth not burden us with a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:102079:52"/> of Ceremonies now, as under the Oeconomy of the Jews under the Legal Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation; yet this one Ceremonie (of Baptiſm) will prove a heavier Yoke to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers now then Circumciſion with all the whole Body of Ceremonies appertaining to that Legal Diſpenſation, in caſe it muſt be Adminiſtred by Dipping and Plunging the whole Body under Water, as Anabaptiſts ſay it muſt.</p>
            <p>I come now to his Metaphors, the firſt whereof (he ſaith) is that of a Burial: For this, he and all of his Perſwaſion quote <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. and <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Buried with him in Baptiſm unto Death.</hi> From this Metaphor of a Burial the Dr. and all his Party, do hold and teach (for an infallible truth) that the Scope and Deſign of the Apoſtle in the two places (now quoted) is to teach and ſet forth the mode and manner how Chriſt was Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, to the end Believers ſhould (in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm) imitate the ſame: This (if I miſtake them not, as I am very confident I do not) is the ſenſe and meaning wherein he and all Anabap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſts take thoſe Scriptures.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer to whom, I affirm that this their ſenſe of thoſe places is ſenſeleſs, and meerly forc't to ſerve their own turn, in proving that Dipping and Plunging (in Baptiſm) is the only true and right Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>Now to diſcover their Miſtake and Error
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:102079:53"/> herein, I ſhall offer but two things to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, to ſhew the Scope and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Apoſtle in thoſe places, which is not (as they fondly and injudiciouſly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine) to ſhew that Chriſt was Baptized by dipping, or that Believers are to be ſo Baptized.</p>
            <p>But the Scope and Deſign of the Apoſtle in thoſe places, is to ſet forth and prove that Suretyſhip Union, which is between Chriſt (the Mediatorial Head) and all the Members of his Body Myſtical; there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no one Act of Obedience, either Active or Paſſive, which Chriſt (the Mediator) performed in the aſſumed Nature, but all his Members are ſaid to do and perform the ſame; and all the Effects and Saving Benefits thereof do undoubtedly redound to all the Elect: and all this is Signified and Sealed in Baptiſm to every Elected Sinner, whether Infant or Adult. And I cannot but reckon it a ſtrange Infatuation on thoſe who lay ſuch ſtreſs on the <hi>Dutch</hi> Tranſlators, in the point of <hi>John</hi> the Dooper, (wherein ſilly and weak People do not a little Glory and Brag) that they ſhould put ſuch Sleights and Contempt on the <hi>Dutch</hi> Annotators, thoſe great Lights of the World, in matter of Infants right to Baptiſm, of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant being a Covenant of abſolute Grace, of Circumciſion being the Initial
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:102079:53"/> Seal thereof, and Baptiſm ſucceeding in the room thereof; with ſundry other material points in Goſpel Religion, wherein they are Sound and Orthodox: Yet, in nothing muſt our Dr. and his Adherents make uſe of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> only <hi>John the Dooper, John the Dooper:</hi> And in this Commiſſion, <hi>de Salve Dopende,</hi> Dipping them.</p>
            <p>And what ground hath our Dr. to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that had our <hi>Engliſh Tranſlators</hi> turned the words (about Baptiſm) into Dipping, as the <hi>Dutch</hi> Tranſlators have done? (If it be as he ſaith) that therefore it muſt (neceſſarily) be ſo in the Original, or how will he prove the <hi>Dutch</hi> Tranſlators nearer to Infallibility than our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlators were? or that our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors would have been more Infallible than they were, in caſe they had Tranſlated <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt Johannes de Dooper;</hi> and in the Commiſſion <hi>Baptizing them, de Salve Dopende</hi> Dipping them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if to imitate and ſet forth Chriſts Burial, be the deſign of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, then muſt it (neceſſarily) follow that it is Mens duty to imitate it in all the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of a Burial, as well as in ſome.</p>
            <p>Chriſt when he was Buried, he was whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Paſſive; he did not go into the Grave himſelf, but was laid in by others; ſo muſt Perſons be in Baptiſm, they muſt be wholly
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:102079:54"/> Paſſive, they muſt not go into the Water <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hemſelves, but muſt be laid under the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by the Adminiſtrator of Baptiſm: Chriſt when Buried was left in the Grave, ſo muſt the Perſon in Baptiſm; he muſt be left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Water as long as Chriſt continued in the Grave, which was three Days and three Nights.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall ſay it is abſurd and ridiculous to think or ſay, that theſe Circumſtances ſhould be attended or imitated by Believers in Water-Baptiſm, I ſay ſo too; ad do farther ſay and affirm, that it is (altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) as abſurd and ridiculous for any to affirm and teach, that for Believers to ſet forth and imitate Chriſts Burial is the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles deſign in the above-mentioned Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: If Anabaptiſts will be peremptory in aſſerting and teaching that to ſet forth and imitate Chriſts Burial in thoſe places, is the ſcope and deſign of the Apoſtle, they muſt give me leave to be as peremptory as they in affirming, that unleſs they imitate Chriſts Burial in the Circumſtances now mentioned, their Baptiſm (about which ſo great and confuſed a noiſe is made in the World) is but a meer ludicrous (or mock) Baptiſm, for that they do not imitate Chriſt in their Baptiſm in thoſe Circumſtances which are ſo eſſentially neceſſary to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:102079:54"/> forth and repreſent his Death and Burial, in caſe it be as they hold it is.</p>
            <p>To which I add, that our Baptizing by pouring out or ſprinkling Water on the Subject, doth (every way) more exactly repreſent and ſet forth a Burial, than that of Dipping and Plunging the whole Body under Water.</p>
            <p>The truth of this will appear, if the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars following be ſeriouſly and without prejudice conſidered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> In Dipping and Plunging into the Water, the Party Baptized, is Active, in going himſelf into the Water, which (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) ought not to be the Ordinance of Water-Baptiſm, being (in all reſpects) a Paſſive Ordinance, wherein the Subject is to be wholly Paſſive, as the Soul is in the Work of Regeneration.</p>
            <p>The Work of Converſion or Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the Inward and Spiritual Baptiſm Adminiſtred by Chriſt. In this wonderful Work, the Dead Sinner hath no hand in effecting or producing the ſame, it is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done by Chriſt, the Adminiſtrator there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. So in the outward Ordinance of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Baptiſm, (which is no more than the outward Sign or Seal of the Inward) the Miniſter of the Goſpel (in Adminiſtring Baptiſm) muſt only be Active, the Subject muſt put forth no Act at all. The Party
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:102079:55"/> going himſelf into the Water, doth not repreſent and ſet forth a Dead Man, in Pouring out or Sprinkling Water on the Subject, the Party is wholly Paſſive, as is a Dead Man when Buried. Again, in Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and Plunging the Party Baptized, is applyed to the Water, not the Water to the Party, which is contrary to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Burials, which all Men know is to lay the Corps on its Back in the Grave, and to Pour out or Sprinkle the Earth on it.</p>
            <p>In Baptizing by Sprinkling or Pouring out Water, the Party is laid on his Back, and the Water poured out or ſprinkled on him.</p>
            <p>The Party Dead is never thruſt into the Earth, but the Earth or Mould is poured out on him.</p>
            <p>Now, whether of theſe two ways of Baptizing by Dipping and Plunging, or that of Pouring out or Sprinkling Water up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, do more lively and exactly ſet forth and repreſent a Burial, let any (who have not loſt their Senſes) Judge.</p>
            <p>As to the ſecond Metaphor, <hi>(viz.)</hi> A Reſurrection, I humbly conceive, that what here follows may ſuffice to ſhew, that as Anabaptiſts do not (at all) hold forth or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>epreſent the Death and Burial of Chriſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir going into the Water (in their way)
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:102079:55"/> ſo, neither do they ſet forth and repreſent his Reſurrection, as they fancy they do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is moſt certain, that when the time (determined by God's Decree) for Chriſt's remaining in a State of Death was accompliſht, (according to the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,) he raiſed up himſelf from the Grave. No Hand of Men or Angels helpt to raiſe him. So that plain it is, if the Scriptures they alledge for this, be to be taken in a literal Senſe, then muſt it needs follow, that as he that Adminiſters Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm (by Dipping or Burying the whole Body under Water,) doth Adminiſter Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm in that way of Burying under the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to the end the Party ſo Baptized might lively ſet forth the Death and Burial of Chriſt; ſo he muſt leave the Party Buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Water, to raiſe up himſelf, that ſo he might repreſent Chriſt in his raiſing up himſelf from the Grave. If this were practiſed, it would not be hard to gueſs, how many Proſelites they would get to join with them in this their Fantaſtical new Mode of Baptizing. And truly, for my part, I cannot ſee how they can be excuſed from doing the one as well as the other, ſeeing that the Metaphor muſt be Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted in all its parts, as well as in ſome. And thus they may ſee what they are like
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:102079:56"/> to get, by building their Confidence on miſunderſtood and wreſted Metaphors.</p>
            <p>I come now to the Doctor's third <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> whereby he labours to prove, that the right way of Baptizing under the Goſpel, is (and muſt be) by Dipping and Plunging the whole Body under Water, <hi>(viz.)</hi> The Practice of the firſt Baptizers. In this he is as full of Confidence as he was in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two; I have now diſmiſt, and I hope in the Goodneſs of God it will plainly be demonſtrated, that (in this alſo) he and his Adherents do pervert the Scriptures, which gives us the account of the firſt Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizers, as they (moſt certainly) do the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scriptures, which they bring to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and make good their Soul deluding Dreams.</p>
            <p>He begins with <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> Page 10. where he tells his Reader, that it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that Dipping is the right way of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing from the firſt Baptizers: The firſt mention (ſaith he) of this Ordinance of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Baptiſm, we have in <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.1. where <hi>John</hi> the Dipper is mentioned; and ſo he goes on in a ſtrange kind of Rapſody, warbling out his ſo much affected Note, Dipping and Plunging. I ſhall not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to follow the Dr. <hi>(Pedetentim)</hi> ſtep by ſtep in his <hi>Pedantick</hi> way, leaſt I ſhould be found guilty of the ſame empty Tauto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:102079:56"/> wherewith his ſo much admired E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle abounds.</p>
            <p>The ground of his miſtake herein, is the wrong Etymology he gives of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which he and his miſtaken Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies take to ſignifie and mean Dipping and Plunging the whole Body under Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>This Etymologie of his I have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, as the Reader may ſee, if he look back to the firſt Head of the Diſpute, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Etymologie of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I ſhall not repeat but go on to confirm the truth of the Etymologie I have given of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from the word of God, and the beſt Greek Authors, by ſuch Arguments as (I hope in Chriſt) will prove irrefragable.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſhall be grounded on the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> his Harmonizing with the Pen-men of the <hi>Old-Teſtament</hi> in all the parts of his Miniſtry, if the Dr. will grant (as he muſt) if he ſpeak truth that his <hi>John the Dooper</hi> was a true and faithful Prophet of God, he muſt of neceſſity grant that <hi>John</hi> did run parallel with <hi>Moſes</hi> and the other Prophets.</p>
            <p>This the Dr. muſt either grant or deny, if he grant that <hi>John</hi> did run exactly paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel with <hi>Moſes</hi> and the other Prophets, then is it beyond all contradiction that <hi>John</hi> adminiſtred Baptiſm by pouring out
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:102079:57"/> or ſprinkling Water on the Perſons he Baptized; for moſt certain it is, that <hi>Moſes</hi> (under the Ceremonial Diſpenſation) did apply all the Legal Waſhings and Purifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by Water, (which all had a Typical relation to Chriſt to come, as <hi>John</hi>'s Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm alſo had) by pouring out or ſprinkling the Water: The Prophets alſo, (witneſs thoſe two great Prophets <hi>Eſa.</hi> and <hi>Ezek.</hi>) they foretold of the manner how God would apply to his People the two great Benefits accrewing by his Sons Mediatorial Sacrifice, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Juſtification and Sanctification, which was to be by Sprinkling, as will evidently appear by <hi>Eſa.</hi> 52.15. <hi>Then ſhall he Sprinkle many Nations,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. <hi>Then will I Sprinkle clean Water upon you,</hi> &amp;c. In theſe places the Spirit of Chriſt (in his Prophets) had an Eye to the Baptiſmal Waſhings of the <hi>New-Teſtament</hi> Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now if <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> did (in all the parts of his Miniſtry) Harmonize with <hi>Moſes</hi> and the other Prophets, he did (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly) Baptize by pouring out or ſprinkling Water on thoſe he Baptized; for moſt certain it is, (as hath been already obſerved) pouring out or ſprinkling was the mode or way of application of all the Ceremonial Waſhings which were uſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>If the Dr. and his Adherents deny that
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:102079:57"/> 
               <hi>John</hi> did run (exactly) parallel with <hi>Moſes</hi> and the other Pen-men of Holy Scriptures, then is <hi>John the Dooper</hi> (by them) made a falſe Prophet; and all who (from <hi>John</hi>) take up and practiſe the mode of Dipping the whole Body under Water, (as the only right Baptiſm) are Self-condemned in that they do (herein) follow one who contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted the Spirit of God in the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</p>
            <p>And ſo (hereby) it appears how much <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> is obliged to the Dippers of our Age, who, (rather than they will loſe their ſilly Opinion) will have the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth to ſpeak Nonſenſe, (yea, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict himſelf) and <hi>John</hi> the greateſt of all the other Prophets, (becauſe the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate fore-runner of Chriſt) to be a falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</p>
            <p>This Stain they will never be able to waſh off their Name, any other way than by honeſtly acknowledging that <hi>John</hi> did (in all the parts of his Miniſtry) Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize with <hi>Moſes</hi> and the other Prophets, the which if they once grant, (as they muſt if they ſpeak by the Holy Ghoſt) then is their Cauſe loſt, and <hi>John</hi> no more to be Stiled <hi>John the Dooper,</hi> but <hi>John</hi> the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizer.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid, I argue thus, if <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> did (in all the parts of his
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:102079:58"/> Miniſtry) Harmonize and agree with <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and the other Prophets, then did he adminiſter Baptiſm by pouring out or ſprinkling Water upon thoſe he Baptized: But <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> did (in all the parts of his Miniſtry) Harmonize and agree with <hi>Moſes</hi> and the other Prophets.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> did adminiſter Baptiſm by pouring out or ſprinkling Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on thoſe he Baptized.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Argument ſhall be grounded on impoſſibility, thus, that way of Baptizing which is impoſſible to be practiſed (without a miraculous ſtrength of Body) was never commanded by Chriſt, nor practiſed by <hi>John;</hi> but to Baptize the many Multitudes which came to <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, by Dipping the whole Body under Water, was a thing altogether impoſſible, ſeeing <hi>John</hi> had no miraculous ſtrength of Body to render him capable of ſuch an arduous and difficult Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration.</p>
            <p>Therefore that way of Baptizing, by Dipping the whole Body under Water, was never commanded by Chriſt, nor practiſed by <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The major Propoſition will not be deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Aſſumption will readily be ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, (as an unqueſtionable truth) if Men who plead for that way of Dipping will be but ingenious in doing two things. Firſt,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:102079:58"/> in lifting up in their Arms (cleverly from the Earth) the many Corpulent-Bodies which offer themſelves to Baptiſm, lay them under the Water, and there hold them until the Adminiſtrator pronounce the words of Inſtitution, <hi>I Baptize thee in the Name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Secondly, in ſincerely acknowledging what experience teaches them concerning this Practice; theſe two Particulars comply'd in, will (I doubt not) put the matter now in Debate out of all Queſtion, that to Baptize in that way of taking up in the Arms, and laying under Water the moſt Corpulent Bodies who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to Baptiſm, and to hold them under the Water till the words of Inſtitution be pronounced; is a thing altogether impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, not only in reſpect of the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrator, whoſe Bodily Strength muſt (in an ordinary way) ſink and fail in lifting and holding up (ſo long) ſuch maſſy, ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous weights: And alſo in reſpect of the Subject, who muſt (undoubtedly) be in great fear and in apparent danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing let fall, if not of being Suffocated or Smothered in the Water.</p>
            <p>And ſtrange it is to me, that Arminians, who plead ſo much for the univerſal Love and Mercy of God to Mankind (in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,) ſhould not ſee how full of Reflection
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:102079:59"/> on God, this Principle of theirs is, which makes the God of Love and Mercy, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of ſuch a Mode or Way of Baptizing, which is not poſſible to be practiſed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out apparent Danger, both to Health and Life, of both the Subject and the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrator too.</p>
            <p>I conclude this Argument with the Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Judicious <hi>Sydenham,</hi> (viz) <hi>That if Baptiſm be to be Adminiſtred in that way of Dipping only, Happy are thoſe who live in hot Climates, or who have Bodies of Braſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A third Argument may be grounded on <hi>Scandal,</hi> thus; That Mode or Way of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing, which is both Immodeſt and tends to Excite Luſtful Motions and Carnal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires in Men and Women, cannot be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Chriſt; neither was the ſame ever practiſed by <hi>John.</hi> But that way of Baptizing by Dipping the whole Body un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Water, is both Immodeſt and tends to Excite Luſtful Motions and Carnal Deſires in Men and Women.</p>
            <p>Therefore that Mode of Baptizing by Dipping the whole Body under Water, was never commanded by Chriſt, neither was the ſame ever practiſed by <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He who commands all Matters (relating to Divine Worſhip) to be done decently, and in order, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. and who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands Believers to abſtain from all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:102079:59"/> of Evil, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.22. can never be the Author of ſuch Diſorderly Practiſes, as thwart and contradict his own general Rules. Now, whether it be not an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſt and unſeemly Sight, to ſee a mixt Company of Men and Women ſtand in Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, (to uſe Mr. <hi>Sydenham</hi>'s Expreſſion) next to Nakedneſs it ſelf: Let any (not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reav'd of common Modeſty) Judge: And whether the Adminiſtrator can (poſſibly) handle the Female Sex, as he doth (when actually Dipping them,) and not feel the riſings and motions of Concupiſcence in his Nature; I leave to Thinking Perſons to Determine and Judge.</p>
            <p>Again, in the fourth place, (to add no more) let the laſt Argument be grounded on the <hi>Analogie,</hi> which is (and muſt be) between the Baptiſm of <hi>John</hi> and that of Chriſt. The Argument is thus framed.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt's way and manner of Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Inward Spiritual Baptiſm (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of that of <hi>John</hi> was but the Outward Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sign) be by Sprinkling or Pouring out upon: Then <hi>John</hi> did (certainly) Baptize by Sprinkling or Powering out the Water on thoſe he Baptized:</p>
            <p>But Chriſt's way and manner of Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Inward Spiritual Baptiſm, is by Sprinkling or Pouring out upon.</p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:102079:60"/>
            <p>Therefore <hi>John</hi> did (certainly) Baptize by Sprinkling or Pouring out Water on thoſe he Baptized.</p>
            <p>If there was a neceſſity that <hi>John</hi> ſhould Harmonize with <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Ceremonial Law and the Prophets, I cannot ſee any reaſon why he ſhould not be as greatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to Harmonize with Chriſt himſelf: And ſeeing that the manner of Chriſt's Adminiſtring the Inward and Spiritual Baptiſm, is by Pouring out and Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Graces of the Spirit upon the Souls of the Elect in the Work of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, why <hi>John</hi> (the forerunner of Chriſt) ſhould Adminiſter his Baptiſm (which was but an External Sign or Chriſt's) by Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or Plunging the whole Body into the Water, can never be demonſtrated by all the Wit and conceited Skill in our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, though he were as well Verſt in all the Roots and Heemantique Nouns of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> Tongue, as his ſo much admired <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertſon</hi> was: And if the Doctor will not be offended, I am very deſirous to know if his ſo highly commended and admired <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertſon</hi> was (by his ſo great Excellency in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> Tongues) more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly acquainted with the Mind of the Holy Ghoſt than other Men; and that Mr. <hi>Robertſon</hi> did certainly believe, that the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:102079:60"/> 
               <hi>Etymology,</hi> which he gave of the word <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizo,</hi> was Infalible as he ſaid. How came it to paſs, that the Learned <hi>Robertſon</hi> did not Renounce that Baptiſm, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in Infancy and by Sprinkling?</p>
            <p>I think I knew Maſter <hi>William Robertſon</hi> as well as Dr. <hi>Ruſſel;</hi> and during the time of my Acquaintance with him, I am ſure, he was far enough from Anabaptiſm. All the Skill he had in the Tongues, with his Acquaintance in the Arts, did not convince him, that the Baptiſm he received in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, and by Sprinkling, was a Nullity, as the Doctor holds it is.</p>
            <p>But to return to <hi>John the Dooper,</hi> I think fit to aſſure the Doctor, that I own my ſelf bound to believe <hi>John</hi> himſelf, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Doctor <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> or any of thoſe Learned Men he ſo greatly Brags of. The words of <hi>John</hi> are ſo plain, that I can ſee no need of a Commentator, to explain their Senſe; he tells us in <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.8. and in <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. that he did Baptize with Water; but that Chriſt ſhould Baptize with the Holy Ghoſt: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, do both intend and ſignify the very ſame way and manner of Adminiſtration: All the difference between <hi>John</hi> and Chriſt, in both their Baptiſms, is in the Subject Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>(viz.)</hi> In the outward Water and the inward Grace: <hi>John</hi> he did Adminiſter
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:102079:61"/> Water, the outward Sign; but Chriſt he did Adminiſter the Spiritual Grace: But as touching the manner, it was (moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly) the very ſame in both.</p>
            <p>Now, if the Doctor grant, (as he muſt if he ſpeak Truth) that Chriſt doth Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the Inward and Spiritual Baptiſm, by Pouring out or Sprinkling the Graces of the Holy Ghoſt, he will find it (altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) Incongruous, and no way agreeing with the <hi>Analogie</hi> of Faith, to hold or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, that <hi>John</hi> did Adminiſter the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Sign in ſuch a manner as was directly contrary to Chriſt. There muſt be (neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily) an Harmonious Agreement between the Sign and the Thing ſignified thereby, which can never be, in caſe Chriſt Baptizes by or with, Pouring out or Sprinkling; and <hi>John</hi> ſhould Baptize by Dipping or Plunging into.</p>
            <p>As Chriſt applies the Graces of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to the Soul in Converſion, not the Soul to the Spirit; ſo in the outward Baptiſm <hi>John</hi> he apply'd the Water (the outward Sign) to the Perſon, not the Perſon to the Water.</p>
            <p>For making the Thing or Point (now in Debate) obvious and plain to the meaneſt Capacity, let it be ſeriouſly conſidered, how plain and expreſs the Scriptures are in affirming, that Chriſt's way or manner in
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:102079:61"/> Adminiſtring the Spiritual Baptiſm, is by Pouring out and Sprinkling the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit on the Souls, which he Regenerates, but never by applying the Souls to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, Read (without prejudice) <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5, 6. <hi>Not by works of righteouſneſs, which we have done, but according to his mercy, he hath ſaved us by the waſhing of regeneration, and the renewing of the holy Ghoſt, which he ſhed on us abundantly, through Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hath powered on us, the very ſame word is made uſe of in <hi>Acts</hi> 2.17. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in the laſt days,</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>I will power out my Spirit on all fleſh,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Both which places are the fulfilling of thoſe Gracious Promiſes in <hi>Eſa.</hi> 44.3. and <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. where the Lord promiſed, that he will pour Water on him that is thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and his Spirit on the Churches Seed. The <hi>Hebrew</hi> word in <hi>Eſa.</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Etzek Ruchi;</hi> and in <hi>Joel</hi> the word uſed to expreſs the ſame thing by, is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Eſhpoch Eth Ruchi:</hi> in neither of which places will our Doctor's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Vetabe lu Otham: And Dip ye them,</hi> be found. The Doctor, the better to help his limping Proſelites over the Stile of Hereſy and Error, tells his Reader, that the Evangeliſt <hi>Matthew</hi> wrote his Goſpel
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:102079:62"/> in the Hebrew Tongue; for Proof where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f, he ſets down his own Opinion, that ſo it is; and this Opinion of his he confirms (as infallible) by the Teſtimony of <hi>Jerom,</hi> and (he thinks) the Opinion of the moſt Learned Men: But the Dr. was ſo wary in this point, that he reſolved the Reader ſhould not (eaſily) find him out in his quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, the which the Dr. knew would eaſily be done, had he (fairly) directed his Reader to the Book and Page in <hi>Jerom;</hi> where his judgment concerning this matter is expreſt, and by Naming the Learned Men, who were one with him and <hi>Jerom</hi> in this Opinion: His neglect herein forces me to charge him with unfairneſs, (to ſay no worſe) if that be a true rule in Logick, <hi>Dolus latet in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalibus,</hi> that Deceit lyes hid in Univerſals; I am ſure the Dr. (as well as the reſt of his Fraternity, (who frequently walk in this Path) muſt fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Laſh; the Drs. lothneſs to Name the Learned Men, who were of his Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this, cauſes me to ſuſpect that he means ſuch as his Learned Baptiſt <hi>Servetus,</hi> and his famous <hi>Caſtellio,</hi> with thoſe other <hi>Arminian</hi> and <hi>Popiſh</hi> Authors, whoſe Names are in his Book.</p>
            <p>It were worth while for the Reader to obſerve what ſhifts the poor Man is put to, to prove and make good (from Gods word)
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:102079:62"/> his new, (though falſly pretended ancient) Mode of Baptizing, by Dipping and Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the whole Body into the Water.</p>
            <p>He tells his Reader that <hi>Matthew</hi> wrote his Goſpel in Hebrew; the Drs. deſign being (no doubt) to make way for his He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and Dip ye them.</hi> The root (ſaith he) is <hi>Tabal,</hi> which is the third Perſon Singular of the <hi>Preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Tenſe,</hi> and ſignifies he Dipped: He Inſtances in <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 5.14. <hi>Then went he down and Dipped himſelf ſeven times in</hi> Jordan, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> From <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> the Dr. comes <hi>(per Saltum)</hi> by a long leap to <hi>John</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ptizing in <hi>Jordan;</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.6. you have (ſaith he) the ſame Words again in the Paſſive Voice, which muſt be rendred in <hi>Engliſh, And were Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of him in</hi> Jordan: And in Ver. 16. you have the ſame root again as it is applied to our Saviour, <hi>And Jeſus when he was Dipped went up ſtraight way out of the Water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Dr. takes for granted, that becauſe <hi>Tabal</hi> ſignifies he Dipped, and that becauſe <hi>Naaman</hi> (in the place above quoted Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped himſelf in <hi>Jordan;</hi> that therefore in <hi>Matthew</hi> it muſt needs be <hi>Vetabelu Otham, and Dip ye them;</hi> and that <hi>John</hi> did Dip all he Baptized, over Head and Ears in <hi>Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:102079:63"/>
            <p>Am I bound to believe that <hi>Matthew</hi> did write his Goſpel in Hebrew, becauſe the Dr. is of the Opinion he did?</p>
            <p>Or, muſt I therefore grant it becauſe <hi>Jerom</hi> is of his Opinion? though neither <hi>Jerom</hi> nor he gives any ſolid reaſons for that their Opinion.</p>
            <p>Two things convince me that both <hi>Jerom,</hi> the Dr. and his pretended Learned Men, were all miſtaken in this their Opinion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I find (by Reading) that the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel which <hi>Matthew</hi> is ſuppoſed to have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Hebrew, was never yet ſeen by any Author, and therefore I muſt mind him of the Maxim, as true and applicable in the preſent caſe, <hi>De non apparentibus, et non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtentibus eadem eſt Ratio,</hi> of things not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, and of things not exiſting, there is the ſame Reaſon to be given.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if <hi>Matthew</hi> had written his Goſpel in Hebrew, he would not have tranſlated into Greek the word <hi>Emmanuel,</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.23. and thoſe whole Sentences, <hi>Eli, Eli, Lamma Sabacthani,</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.46.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe I ſhould (for Argument ſake) grant (which I utterly deny, and challenge the Dr. to make good) that <hi>Matthew</hi> had Written his Goſpel in the Hebrew Tongue, doth it therefore follow (neceſſarily) that the Holy Ghoſt, (who is ſo exact and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:102079:63"/> in chooſing the moſt apt and fit words, whereby to expreſs his Mind) ſhould uſe the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tabal,</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies to Dip, and not the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Rachatz,</hi> which ſignifies to Waſh, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Kibbem,</hi> which ſignifies the ſame: I have already demonſtrated from the word of God, that in all the places of the <hi>New-Teſtament</hi> where the Holy Ghoſt makes mention of Baptiſm, he doth it by the Derivative <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies to Waſh, by pouring out or ſprinkling Water upon, but never by the Primitive <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Bapto,</hi> which ſignifies to Dip or Plunge into: And when the Holy Ghoſt expreſſeth the Act of Dipping or Plunging into, he doth it by the Primitive <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies to Dip into, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver by the Derivative <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies to waſh with; by which it plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears (to me at leaſt) that rather than the Dr. will looſe his Credit and ſuffer his rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Cauſe to be loſt, he will rather open door to the old <hi>Babel</hi> confuſion of Tongues, reſolving (Jeſuit like) to ſet the Pen-men of Holy Scripture together by the Ears, and impoſe on his credulous Reader a real Belief, that what the Holy Ghoſt hath laid down (and plainly expreſt) in Greek, he hath gainſaid and contradicted in Hebrew; which Contradiction can never befall the Pen-men of the Holy Scripture, nor (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:102079:64"/> Blaſphemy) be charged on that Holy Spirit, by which they were Acted and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly Inſpired.</p>
            <p>The reaſon which <hi>Jierom</hi> gives why <hi>Matthew</hi> writ his Goſpel in Hebrew, <hi>(viz.)</hi> for the Sake of thoſe Jews which Believed, is no reaſon at all; for had it been the Will of God it ſhould be ſo, I know no reaſon why <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> (who all three wrote to the Jews, which Believed) ſhould write in Greek, not in Hebrew; witneſs the two Epiſtles of <hi>Peter,</hi> the Epiſtle of <hi>James,</hi> and that of <hi>Paul</hi> to the Hebrews.</p>
            <p>The Dr. pleaſeth himſelf in telling his Reader, that in Mr. <hi>William Robertſon</hi>'s Hebrew <hi>New-Teſtament,</hi> he finds theſe words between the 18th and 19th Verſes (of <hi>Mat.</hi> 28 he means) <hi>And as my Father hath ſent me, even ſo alſo I ſend you. Go ye therefore,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe words he ſets down in the Hebrew Character, telling his Reader that he finds them not in any Greek Copy.</p>
            <p>An Argument (thinks he) that <hi>Matthew</hi> wrote his Goſpel in Hebrew! a meer <hi>Non-ſequitur:</hi> What though thoſe words be not in <hi>Matthew,</hi> I hope he will not deny that they are in <hi>Jo.</hi> 20.21. there the Spirit of God hath recorded them; and why the Dr. ſhould look to find them in <hi>Matthew</hi> I know no reaſon, or wherefore his Learned
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:102079:64"/> Friend Mr. <hi>Robertſon</hi> ſhould take on him to place the Words recorded by <hi>John,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the 18th and 19th of <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive: But whatever moved <hi>Robert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to ſo preſumptuous an Act, in taking on him to alter things of this Nature, (as if by his Skill (in the Hebrew Tongue) he thought himſelf able to rectifie the Order, in which the Holy Ghoſt hath ſet down his own Mind in Writing) I doubt not but the Dr. was well pleaſed with ſo Palpable an Aberration; and all for the love and liking he hath to his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tabal,</hi> he Dipped, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Velammddu,</hi> Diſciple ye. By what I have ſaid, it is eaſie to judge, that could the Dr. but have his will in two things. Firſt, that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Baptizo,</hi> doth alway ſignifie the very ſame thing with its Primitive <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And Secondly, that <hi>Matthew</hi> did write his Goſpel in the Hebrew Tongue, and that the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Vetabelu otham,</hi> and Dip ye them, were the very words of <hi>Matthew.</hi> All the Art in Men and Angels could never hinder but that Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the whole Body under the Water, muſt needs be the only right way of admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the outward Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>But both theſe (on which he erects his tottering ſtructure of Anabaptiſm) I utterly deny, and do fairly offer, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:102079:65"/> promiſe him, that if he can confute (by Gods Word) the Arguments laid down, to prove him miſtaken in both, I will forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with) renounce my Baptiſm received in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy and by Sprinkling, as a meer Nullity; and not only ſo, but I will in Pulpit and Print too, Declare (to the World) that I am fully convinced that Dipping the whole Body (under Water) is the only right way of adminiſtring Water-Baptiſm under the <hi>New-Teſtament</hi> Diſpenſation.</p>
            <p>And this, (I hope with the offer made him, in clearing up the <hi>Etymology</hi> of the word <hi>Baptizo</hi>) will prove as generous an offer as he made to Maſter <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As touching what is (uſually) Objected from <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.16. concerning Chriſt's co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming up out of the Water. And from <hi>Acts</hi> 8.38, 39. concerning <hi>Philip</hi> and the Eunuch going down into, and coming up again out of the Water; I need ſay but two things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> For any to affirm (poſſitively) what the Word of God affirms not, is (to me) a ſure Argument of an Ignorant, Raſh and Preſumptuous Spirit. Reader, mark the words: <hi>And Jeſus, when he was Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, went up ſtraightway out of</hi> (Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from not out of) <hi>the water.</hi> The Text doth not ſay, (in downright Terms) that Chriſt was Dipt under the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:102079:65"/> Water; neither doth it appear from <hi>Acts</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.38, 39. that the Eunuch was Dipt, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Doctor (and his Adherents) will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve it to be ſo, right or wrong.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is nothing more certain than that a Perſon may be ſaid (properly enough) to go down into the Water, though he go not in above Shooe (or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle) deep, which (I doubt not) was pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by both <hi>John</hi> and by <hi>Philip,</hi> in the places above-mentioned; and that for the better conveniency of catching hold of the Water with their Hands, in order to Sprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle or Pour out the ſame on thoſe they Baptized.</p>
            <p>And that which may convince any Man, (not prepoſſeſt with Prejudice againſt the Truth I here contend for) that this was the Practiſe of <hi>John,</hi> and all the firſt Baptizers, (ſo much brag'd of by the Dr.) is the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility of the Spirit's being the Author of any (though the leaſt) Contradiction in any part of God's Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Hence I argue. That which can no way be prov'd or made good by expreſs Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of God's Word, or deduced there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from by ſound (and neceſſary) Conſequence, is an Invention in God's Worſhip, which God will Reject and Abominate as not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by him.</p>
            <p>But Dipping the whole Body under Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:102079:66"/> in Baptiſm, can no way be prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> made good by expreſs Teſtimony of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Word, nor yet by ſound (or neceſſar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Conſequence deduced therefrom.</p>
            <p>Therefore Dipping the whole Body u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der Water (in Baptiſm) is an Invention in God's Worſhip, which God will Reject and Abominate, becauſe not appointed by him.</p>
            <p>The major Propoſition will not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied. That which ſecures the Minor, and proves the Concluſion to be the Truth, (which all the Wit of the Adverſary will never be able to prevail againſt) is the Scriptures ſilence, in that it no where gives an expreſs Witneſs (or Teſtimony) heret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> And the Impoſſibility of that being prov'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a ſound Conſequence (from God's Word,) which makes God the Author of Self-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction.</p>
            <p>The Word of God no where commands Dipping in Baptiſm, neither doth it ſay (in expreſs terms,) that either <hi>John</hi> or any of the Apoſtles did Baptize by Dipping under the Water. Reader! Keep the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary cloſe to this, where doth the word <hi>Dip</hi> appear, either in the command of Chriſt, (when ſpeaking of Baptizing) or in any Inſtance of Perſons Baptized by <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or the Apoſtles? If thou keep cloſe to this, the Enemy will retreat and fly to Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
<pb facs="tcp:102079:66"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the which, if he doth, (as no doubt he will) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> purſue him with a Holy Courage, be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of his daring Brags. How do yo prove, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſound and Scriptural Conſequence, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Holy Spirit of God the Author of Self-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>adiction?</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat thus it is, will (evidently) appear, the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſary can no way avoid it. If thou urge, (with an Holy Zeal for Truth) what is (Graphically) ſet down in God's own Word, concerning the manner of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Blood of the Sacrifices, and the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Purifications, both which had a Typical Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Spiritual Baptiſm, Adminiſtred by the Spirit of Chriſt. Theſe were applied under the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial Adminiſtration, by Sprinkling, not by Dipping, (as hath been before obſerved.) The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who foretold of Chriſt, and the great Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits which ſhould come by him to Believers under the Goſpel. They ſet it forth by Sprinkling, witneſs <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa.</hi> 52.15. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. and in the Goſpel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e are aſſured, that the Spirit of Chriſt doth apply <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he inward Spiritual Baptiſm, by Sprinkling or Pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the Graces of his Spirit on the Soul in the Work of Regeneration, ſee <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.6.</p>
            <p>Now to affirm, that Chriſt either commands Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, or that he (himſelf) was Dipp'd in Baptiſm, what is it, but to affirm, that Chriſt's Spirit doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict himſelf? What is pretended (for Dipping) from <hi>John</hi> 3.23. hath nothing in it to help their Cauſe, but what empty Conceit and Unſcriptural Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence ſupply. <hi>John</hi> (ſaith the Adverſary) <hi>was Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing in</hi> Aenon, <hi>becauſe there was much Water there: Therefore he Baptized by Dipping the whole Body under the Water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſtreſs (or weight) of the Argument is laid on a fond Conceit, that much Water (there) ſignifies and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ports Greatneſs and Depth of Water, which (plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) appears to be otherwiſe, witneſs the <hi>Greek,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:102079:67"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Many Waters denoting ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Rivulets or Springs of Water, wherewith tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> abounded, than that the Waters of that place deep. And it was (I doubt not) for Convenienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that <hi>John</hi> left <hi>Bethabarah,</hi> (a place of deeper V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> becauſe <hi>Aenon</hi> was (every way) more convenien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> commodious for the multitudes o People, which o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> daily to his Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Piſcator</hi>'s Note upon the place, may not (here) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> either improper or impertinent to the Purpoſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hand, <hi>Videntur ſignificari plures Rivi, non autem unu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Magnum Flumen. Many Rivulets, not one gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or Water, ſeems (here) to be ſignified,</hi> ſaith that Lear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed Author; with whom agrees the beſt Geographe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who give the Deſcription of that place.</p>
            <p>I conclude my Treatiſe (againſt Dipping in Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſm) with that Saying of Godly) and Judicious) <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>denham: If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>there be any abſolute need of Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ping, it is to cool the heat of thoſe Mens Spirits, who de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Baptiſm to be true (or right) Baptiſm, becauſe not A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miniſtred by Plunging or Dipping.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reader! Obſerve, that as in the Sacrament of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord's Supper, it is not ſo much the Quantity of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Wine drunk in that Ordinance, (by a Believer) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Quality, which ſignifies and repreſents the Bloo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Chriſt doth not tye a Believer up to ſuch or ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a quantity of Win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be drunk in remembrance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Blood-ſhed, but (only) commands Wine to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> drunk, leaving to the Diſcretion of the Believ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what quantity to drink.</p>
            <p>So in Water-Baptiſm it is not the depth or qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tity of Water which is neceſſary to right Baptiſm, real Water; it matters not how ſmall the quant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be, ſo there be but a Sprinkling (or Pouring out) Water on the Subject, to repreſent the Sprinkli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> (or Pouring out) of the Graces of God's Spirit on t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Elect Soul in Effectual Calling.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102079:67"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
